<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Popery, the grand apostasie being the substance of certain sermons preached on 2 Thes. 2, v.1 to 12 on occasion of the discovery of that desparate plot of the papists against the King, kingdom and the Protestant religion / by John Troughton ...</title>
            <author>Troughton, John, 1637?-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 215 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63267</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23765</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07896310</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07896310</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40317</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63267)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40317)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1216:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Popery, the grand apostasie being the substance of certain sermons preached on 2 Thes. 2, v.1 to 12 on occasion of the discovery of that desparate plot of the papists against the King, kingdom and the Protestant religion / by John Troughton ...</title>
                  <author>Troughton, John, 1637?-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>166 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Thessalonians, 2nd, II, 1-12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40317:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40317:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>POPERY The Grand APOSTASIE: Being the Subſtance of certain SERMONS</p>
            <p>Preached on 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 1. to 12. On occaſion of the diſcovery of the deſperate <hi>Plot</hi> of the Papiſts, againſt the King, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Troughton</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>To which is added a Sermon on <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. preached <hi>November</hi> 5. 1678.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers Chapel.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:40317:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40317:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was well obſerved by one, That next to the knowledge of Chriſt and of the true way of ſalvation by him, nothing is more neceſſary for a Chriſtian, than the knowledge of Antichriſt: for hereby he may be
<pb facs="tcp:40317:3"/>able to diſtinguiſh the true knowledge of Chriſt, from the corruptions and mixture with which Antichriſt hath adulterated and obſcured the true Doctrine of the Goſpel. That the <hi>Pope</hi> with his Adherents is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt hath been the general opinion of learned men for theſe laſt <hi>600.</hi> Years, ever ſince <hi>Gregory 7.</hi> not of Proteſtants only, <hi>Hus, Wicleff,</hi> and the <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> but alſo of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that lived and dyed in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Roman Church. And ſeeing our Papiſts generally confeſs Antichriſt in St. <hi>Johns</hi> epiſtle to be the ſame with the man of ſin in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and with the myſtical <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> in the <hi>Apoc.</hi> they do in effect yield that the Pope is Antichriſt, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the marks of the two latter
<pb facs="tcp:40317:3"/>do undeniably agree to him. For this cauſe I have waved the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar controverſies, betwixt us and the Papiſts, which have been ſo largely and clearly managed by our Writers, both formerly and of late, as leſs neceſſary for this preſent time; there being little of reaſon, conſcience, or Scripture to urge any Proteſtant to embrace any particular error or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the Papiſts, endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing briefly and ſummarily to ſhew that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is, as <hi>Wicleff</hi> long ſince called it, the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Satan, myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> a ſtate of Apoſtate Chriſtians that have joyned themſelves to the Pope as their Head againſt Chriſt, his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel and pure Church; that by this brief conſideration of things Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb facs="tcp:40317:4"/>may be the more ſtirred up to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, and to oppoſe in their places that body of men which call themſelves the only Catholick Church, that they may be the more zealous for the truth as it is received in the Reformed Churches; and that they may if cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to it, ſuffer with the greater comfort what cruelties and violence God may yet permit that Beaſt of <hi>Rome</hi> to exerciſe upon his Church. I my ſelf, and many that heard this diſcourſe, have thought it might be ſeaſonable and uſeful in theſe days to plain and private Chriſtians (for the learned have no need of it) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe through long peace and ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the error and tyranny of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts have been much forgotten by the people, and many that hate the name
<pb facs="tcp:40317:4"/>of Papiſts ſcarce know the grounds they ſtand on, and are Antipapiſts by a kind of implicite faith. If any find their judgements informed, their conſciences ſettled, their zeal and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage excited by theſe endeavours, in theſe ſhaking times, I have mine end; and may they and the Church of Chriſt long enjoy that benefit to the glory of God and their own comfort, to the ſtrengthening of their brethren and the ſhame of their implacable and reſtleſs adverſaries.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the work of the Goſpel,</hi> J. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:40317:5"/>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:40317:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 THES. 2.</hi> v. <hi>1. to 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Now we beſeech you Brethren by the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and by our gathering together unto him: <hi>v. 2.</hi> That you be not ſoon ſhak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in mind or be troubled neither by Spirit, nor by word, nor by letter, as from us, as that the day of Chriſt is at hand. <hi>v. 3.</hi> Let no man deceive you by any means: for that day ſhall not come except there come a falling away firſt: and [that] man of ſin be revealed, the ſon of perdition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words begin a new diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and contain an earneſt obteſtation to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> not to be troubled at the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of ſome, that the day of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> his ſecond coming, was at hand: which though in appearance it tended to holineſs and watchfulneſs, to make men
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40317:6"/>live in preparation for Chriſts coming; yet, ſeeing his coming was not nigh, and many great things were to be tranſacted firſt both in the world and the Church; this perſwaſion would take off Chriſtians from their repective duties, in the ſeveral places and times they ſhould live in; and would give great occaſion to Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtical mockers to think and ſay Chriſt would never come, ſeeing his coming was ſo long delaied beyond expectation of his ſervants; and conſequently that all the Goſpel was a fable, and Religion vain, which alſo was foretold, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. v. 3, 4. <hi>In the laſt days ſhall come Scoffers, walking after their own luſts, ſaying Where is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of his coming? for ſince the Fathers fell aſleep all things continue as they were.</hi> The Apoſtle therefore beſeecheth them by the coming of Chriſt and our gathering to him, <hi>i. e.</hi> As ſure as they did believe Chriſt would come, and his Saints ſhould be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to him, ſo alſo to believe that his coming was not nigh; but that great tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions and changes ſhould come before that day. Or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> may be well rendered, I beſeech you for the ſake of the coming of our Lord, and our ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering to him, <hi>i. e.</hi> that you may not bring this Doctrine of Chriſts coming
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40317:6"/>into Queſtion when the world ſhall ſee you are miſtaken in the time when you looked for it.</p>
            <p>That you be not ſoon ſhaken, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> That you be not unſetled or made to fluctuate in your minds, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nor be perplexed. This is the obteſtation.</p>
            <p>Next the Apoſtle ſignifies the means, how this perplexing Doctrine was intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced amongſt them: <hi>viz.</hi> By ſpirit, by word, or by pretence of his <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> v. 2.</p>
            <p>Then renewing his obteſtation, <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>Let no man deceive you by any means,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by any pretence whatſoever; he entereth upon the confutation of this opinion, telling them that Chriſt would not come, till there had been an Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in the Church, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is an <hi>Ellipſis,</hi> wherein ſomething for brevity ſake is omitted: For except there come an Apoſtaſie firſt, it is to be ſupplyed from the firſt <hi>v. The day of Chriſt ſhall not come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Afterwards he deſcribeth the manner and meaſure of this Apoſtaſie, to <hi>v.</hi> 12. Hence we may obſerve by way of intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.</p>
            <p>Obſ. 1. <hi>That the Church even in the beſt ages of it hath been infeſted with errours and diſturbances.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:40317:7"/>
            <p>The Church of old under <hi>Moſes,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after their deliverance out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> and their receiving the Law from God by an audible voice, did preſently return to the Idolatry of <hi>Egypt</hi> in the worſhip of the <hi>Golden Calf,</hi> Ex. 32.1, 2. though they had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged themſelves to the Lord by Covenant, a few days before, <hi>chap.</hi> 24.3, 6, 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And all his time he was wearied with their ill carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. And in the times of the Prophets, there were uſually falſe Prophets ſeducing the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. Our Saviour foretold <hi>falſe Chriſts</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> ſhould ariſe ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his days, Mat. 24.24. And his Apoſtles, that there ſhould be <hi>falſe teachers</hi> in the Church, <hi>privily bringing in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them,</hi> and that <hi>many ſhould follow their pernicious ways,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 2.</p>
            <p>The Primitive times, as they were moſt happy. in Zeal and affection in the ſound and Orthodox profeſſours; ſo they were as unhappy in the manifold errors, Sects, diviſions that did diſturb them, as any of theſe latter Ages. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> hath given us a Catalogue of 80. Hereſies that troubled the Church in thoſe days;<note place="margin">Auguſt. <hi>Lib. de Haer.</hi> ad Quod vult Deus.</note> and yet he ſaith he omitted many and named but the principal.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:40317:7"/>
            <p>It appears by their Epiſtles, that the Apoſtles had no ſooner planted Churches, but the weeds of errors and opinions did ſtraight ways ſpring up amongſt them: and this chiefly by theſe three means here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By pretence of the ſpirit. When God did afford his ſpirit in extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gifts and revelations to his Prophets and Apoſtles, there never wanted men who pretended to the ſame ſpirit, and the like revelations for their own devices; moſt of them wilfully feigning, ſome ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially and ſome by diabolical means procuring revelations and Enthuſiaſms; and ſome weakly miſtaking their own fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and ſtrong perſwaſions for dictates and inſpirations of the Holy Ghoſt. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>Believe not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits, whether they are of God: for many falſe prophets are gone out into the world,</hi> ſuch as pretended to the ſpirit, and that to the ſubverſion of the greateſt truths in the Goſpel, even to deny the perſon, and coming of Jeſus Chriſt, as <hi>Simon Magus</hi> and his followers; therefore he ſubjoyneth this mark, <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>Every ſpirit that confeſſeth that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is of God:</hi> and every ſpirit that confeſſeth that he is not come, is not of God. The ſame direction is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40317:8"/>given, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2, 3. <hi>I give you to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that no man ſpeaking by the ſpirit of God calleth Jeſus accurſed:</hi> Such it ſeems there were, that preten ding to the ſpirit the Apoſtles had, rejected and reviled Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By pretence of a word or oral tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They that could not pretend the ſpirit ſpeaking in themſelves, pretended the judgment and ſayings of Chriſt and his Apoſtles when abſent, for their own opinions, ſometimes forging their ſayings, ſometimes miſtaking the meaning of them, affixing their own ſence to them. Thus a tradition was received, as coming from the mouth of Chriſt, that the beloved Diſciple ſhould not die, <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.22, 23. and is yet believed in the <hi>Greek</hi> Church who ſhew a place near <hi>Epheſus</hi> where they ſay that Apoſtle when old commanded himſelf to be buried alive; where by ſome eſtuation or bubling of the earth they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude he ſtill breatheth. St. <hi>Paul</hi> was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten troubled by the Judaizing Chriſtians, who would have kept up the ceremonial law, pretending the authority and practice of <hi>Peter,</hi> and other Apoſtles that lived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews;</hi> which he refuteth at large, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. And it appeareth by almoſt all <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles that this tradition was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40317:8"/>importunately urged and ſcattered through all the Churches by that ſort of men, even when the Apoſtles and Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> had declared, that they never commanded ſuch doctrine to be preached, <hi>Acts</hi> 25.24.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, By the pretence of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, [our Epiſtle in the text.] And this either by pretence of forged Scripture, or falſe and forced interpretations of the true Canonical writings. Of the former ſort were the writings of the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and thoſe fabulous Legends of <hi>Tobit, Judith, Suſannah, &amp;c.</hi> which were never received by the Jewiſh Church. And ſuch were the many ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitious writings in the primitive times, as the Goſpel of <hi>Peter, Andrew, Thomas, Nicodemus,</hi> and almoſt of all the Apoſtles; the Goſpel and Epiſtle of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceans,</hi> the Liturgie of <hi>James,</hi> and the like, mentioned by <hi>Euſebius</hi> and other writers. Of the latter ſort the Apoſtle ſpeaketh 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15, 16. That there were many unlearned and unſtable Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans who did wreſt ſome hard places in <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles and the other Scriptures to their own deſtruction; of this kind is this in the text as ſome ſuppoſe,<note place="margin">Cartwr. in Locum.</note> that this opinion of Chriſts coming to judgment
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40317:9"/>was raſhly collected by ſome, from thoſe words in the former Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſ. ch.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>We that are alive and remain unto the coming of our Lord, ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent thoſe that are aſleep:</hi> hence they thought that the Apoſtle ſuppoſed that at leaſt ſome of them who were then alive might live to the coming of Chriſt. Though it ſeems that all theſe three means of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended revelations, traditions and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were uſed for this doctrine.</p>
            <p>Theſe arts have been all along uſed to diſturb the Church and to pervert ſouls. The <hi>Gnoſticks, Montanus</hi> and <hi>Manes</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended their inſpired revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">Cont. Haer. De praeſer.</note> and many others in latter ages. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> tell us that many of the Hereticks of their days pretended traditions from one Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle or other for their doctrine and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; as alſo others had their <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Scriptures or Canonical texts miſapplied to maintain their errors.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts make great uſe of all three of theſe pretences to eſtabliſh their groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt errors. The doctrine of the real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt in the bread, of the worſhip of Saints and of religious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Images is mainly built upon Revelations, dreams and apparitions.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40317:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Lindanus</hi> ingenuouſly confeſſed that all thoſe doctrines and practices wherein the Proteſtants do oppoſe them, and diſſent from them, are to be proved by traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Apoſtles, not from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Their doctrines of Purgatory, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Angels, equivocations and diſſemblings are proved by the book of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, Judith, Suſan. &amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtles Canons, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed from 50 to 85, in the laſt age, do them great ſervices in the matters of their diſcipline: and ſometimes they wreſt Scriptures for their purpoſe; but they have been ſo baffled and ſhamed out of this ſince the Bible hath been common and ſtudied by Proteſtants, that they have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken this hold, and the Jeſuites think the poor ſecular Prieſts have betrayed their cauſe by undertaking to diſpute for it out of the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Theſe troubles by errors ariſe from the weakneſs of ſome who have more zeal than judgment, and uſually deſire new things,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16. 2 Tim. 4.3.</note> People unlearned and unſtable and that have itching ears; from pride and conceit in others, who that they may ſeem wiſer than their brethren, will be wiſe above or againſt what is written: ſome teach perverſe things to draw diſciples after them; ſome
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40317:10"/>for ſecular intereſt. There was no other reaſon why the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> imbraced the worſhip of images, tranſubſtantiation and ſome ſuch doctrines, but becauſe the promoters of them did alſo promote their authority and ſtrengthen their hands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Godly and moſt ſerious part of the Church. But the moſt uſual cauſes of errors are ignorance of the Scriptures, and of the principles of religion founded on them (which in the primitive times had a great occaſion given it by the prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate opinions that new Converts brought from Judaiſme and Paganiſme, and from the new Teſtament not being fully written in a conſiderable time, and the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral books thereof not gathered into one volume in a long ſpace after) and chiefly corrupt affections: Men will imbrace er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors becauſe they love not the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. This ſheweth the neceſſity of adhering to the Scripture, and of a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſtry. If we ſtick not to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the pretence of the Spirit and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions will lead us into a wilderneſs where there is no end. Heathens, Mahometans, Papiſts and all Enthuſiaſts will diſtract us by their ſeveral and contrary pretenſions. And if there be not a ſtanding and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Miniſtry, Apocryphal Scriptures, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40317:10"/>falſe interpretations of Scripture will eaſily beguile the unskilful and hinder the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the more wiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Papiſt's brags of infallibility of the Pope or Church, and the neceſſity of it to the foundation of our faith, is as fooliſh as it is untrue: The Apoſtles and Apoſtolical men were infallible, and yet this will not prevent errors and Hereſies of the higheſt nature either in their own or in the next ſucceeding ages. An infallible head or guide will not ſecure the Church from errors and diviſions, unleſs all the people be infallible likewiſe, certainly able to diſcern the truth declared to them, and perfectly free from all evil affections which may hinder their receiving and ſubmitting to the truth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is no Wonder to ſee errors and diviſions in theſe laſt days of the Church, ſith they were in the firſt. While men are ſubject to ignorance and evil affections, there will be both errors and diviſions; and if we go to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to avoid all errors and <hi>Schiſms</hi> (becauſe they boaſt of ſuch Unity, which was never promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nor long enjoyed by any Church) we ſhall but do like Children that tear ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny little holes in a garment into one great one that comprehends them all and more and cannot be repaired.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:40317:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 2. It is certainly foretold that there ſhould be an Apoſtaſie in the Church.</p>
            <p>The ſame Apoſtle almoſt in the ſame words foretels it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <hi>The ſpirit ſpeaks expreſly that ſome ſhall depart from the faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Chriſtians might be apt to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the coming of Chriſt, and their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting reſt to be at hand, from the love and joy they had conceived upon their firſt receiving the Goſpel, but they are here told [that] happy time is not ſo nigh.</p>
            <p>There muſt come a departure of many from the faith firſt, and many conteſts and perſecutions ſhould enſue thence; and therefore they ſhould arm themſelves with patience to a conflict before they muſt expect the Crown. When God made the world, he made it wonderful great and large, and ſtored it with almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite variety of creatures to ſet forth his own Majeſty; he hath alſo continued it ſome thouſands of years with as great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of providences in his governing of it, to ſhew his manifold wiſdom, power, mercy, and juſtice; and what will be the wonderful tranſactions of the world to come through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eternity to ſet forth the glory of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ernal God, no creature can conceive.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40317:11"/>In like manner when our Lord came from Heaven to purchaſe a Church to ſerve him, it was not quickly to expire, but to conflict with the world and the Devil, with enemies without and within, through many changes and viciſſitudes a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable time; and at laſt through faith and patience to inherit the promiſes. It was long that the Church continued under the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of the Law; and there were many changes and declinings of it at ſeveral times under the Judges and Kings of <hi>Judah:</hi> but there was one great Apoſtaſie of the Ten tribes under <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> which ended in the ruin of that State and people. Such a departure was there to be in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church, ſignified here by the indeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate word, <hi>There ſhall come a departure or Apoſtaſie:</hi> for the falling off of a few par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons was no ſtrange thing, but happened in every age. Now ſuch Apoſtaſies are permitted,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To puniſh the ingratitude of men for the Goſpel. Becauſe they receive not the love of the truth: becauſe Chriſt and his Goſpel are not welcome to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of men; but any or no religion would content them as well, if they might have outward peace and proſperity, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt ſuffers them to be inticed with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40317:12"/>Errors and Hereſies to their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, which at laſt bring publick ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities and ruin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To puniſh the Hypocriſie of others. Some pretend great zeal and affection in the peace of the Church, which is either meerly pretended for worldly intereſt, or but a light and tranſient paſſion (as in the ſtony ground) who can never be perſwaded to be zealous and rooted Chriſtians;<note place="margin">Matth. 13.20.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when they have been tryed a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient time, opportunities of backſliding are ſufferred to come to diſcover and ſhame them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To manifeſt and honour thoſe that are ſound. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18, 19. There muſt be hereſies among you, that they which be approved may be made manifeſt among you. When peace and truth meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſound and beſt Chriſtians are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, and for the moſt part leſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded than the Hypocrites, that make more ſhew and noiſe; Chriſt therefore ſuffers apoſtaſies to come, to diſcover and honour his ſincere, humble, diligent, and ſtedfaſt ſervants.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Errors are alſo permitted to clear the trut more, and make them that are ſound more ſtedfaſt and ſtrong. The truths of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40317:12"/>the Goſpel have in all ages been prejudiced by the zeal and good affection of ſome well minded, as well as by the oppoſition of enemies, becauſe their affection over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run their judgment and their care to get a diſtinct knowledge of the principles of religion: but the appearance of errours and corruptions makes them more careful to ſearch the truth, which hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways more cleared and fortified by occaſion of the oppoſitions againſt it, and thoſe who are upright have been put upon getting a clearer knowledge of the grounds of their faith, worſhip, and practices thereby.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And in all this Chriſt manifeſteth his diſtinguiſhing grace to ſome, and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgments upon others, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.22. <hi>Behold therefore the goodneſs and ſeverity of God: on them which fell, ſeverity; but towards thee goodneſs, if thou continue in his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Hereby all are ſtirred up to diligence and watchfulneſs. When there ſhall come a falling away of many, all are warn'd thereby to take care how they ſtand leſt they alſo fall.<note place="margin">Rom. 11.20</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Be not therefore ſupri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at, diſcouraged or tempted by, the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſies of others. Though the Church be fair as the Moon, ſhe hath alſo many dark ſpots;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40317:13"/>though clear as the Sun, ſhe hath her clouds and Eclipſes. Many will be carryed away with errour, ſuperſtitions, and carnal po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies; yea ſome of all ſorts; rulers, as well as ruled; learned, as well as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned: Thoſe that have made great ſhew, as well as the common ſort: be not troubled nor ſuſpect the true doctrine and worſhip; theſe things are foretold and therefore muſt be.</p>
            <p>We are next to enquire what this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture is, which is here foretold; and who be guilty of it. Some have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it of the defection of the world from the Roman Empire, following the conjecture of ſome one leader without conſideration (as <hi>Calvin</hi> obſerves) And the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> recede from it very unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and under correction of their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, but the Apoſtles ſaith, <hi>the day of Chriſt ſhallnot come except there come a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture firſt, viz.</hi> a departure from Chriſt The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, here uſed for depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or apoſtaſie, is appropriated to ſignify a defection in or from religion: ſo the ſame Apoſtle uſeth it, but with an explication, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſome ſhall depart from the faith.</hi> Moreover the head of this Apoſtaſie is to ſit in the Temple, the Church of God, <hi>v.</hi> 4. and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40317:13"/>to bring it about by deluſions and lying miracles, ſeducing thoſe that loved not the truth that they might be ſaved, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, <hi>v.</hi> 10, 11, 12. It muſt therefore be a departure from the truth and purity of the Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. It is agreed betwixt Papiſts and Proteſtants that it is the apoſtaſie under Antichriſt as the chief head and leader of it, which is here foretold: but the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, who is this Antichriſt? Where and when this apoſtaſie may be found? As the <hi>Jews</hi> did generally expect the coming of Chriſt, yet knew him not, believed him not, when he was among them; ſo the Papiſts believe and expect that Antichriſt ſhall come, and miſerably ſpoil the Church, but cannot or will not ſee and own him, though he is and long hath been amongſt them.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Nero</hi> ſhall riſe again and be the Antichriſt, as he was the firſt perſecuting Emperour, I not worth the refuting.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts generally teach that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt is yet to come, and ſhall endure but three years and a half, immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the end of the world: that he ſhall be a <hi>Jew</hi> of the tribe of <hi>Dan;</hi> rebuild <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the Temple; aboliſh the Chriſtian worſhip, and almoſt the name
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40317:14"/>of Chriſt: but all this without any colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or proof, except that ſlender one that he ſhall ſit in the temple of God, <hi>v.</hi> 4. Some few are ſo ingenuous as to confeſs that <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>Babylon,</hi> Antichriſts ſeat: but then ſome ſay the Heathen perſecuting Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in the firſt three hundred years of the Church, were this Manof ſin. Some again, conſidering that it is an apoſtaſie of profeſſing Chriſtians here ſpoken of, conjecture that ſome Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> at the end of the world ſhall deny Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an Infidel, and cauſe himſelf to be worſhipped as God; this ſhould be this man of ſin. But the Text plainly ſpeaks of, a defection of Chriſtians which was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly working in the Apoſtles days, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome thing hindered its prevailing and full diſcovery, <hi>vi.</hi> 6, 7, 8. <hi>The myſtery of iniquity doth already work,</hi> and it was to be a myſterious defection, not an open and totall apoſtaſie from Chriſt: it was to be brought in by ſigns, miracles, lying won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and all ungodly deceits, for the juſt condemnation of them that received not the love of the truth that they might be ſaved, though they received the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of it, <hi>v.</hi> 9. to 12. And the man of ſin the Head of this apoſtaſie was to ſit or rule in the Temple of God, which is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40317:14"/>his Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. Therefore this apoſtaſie was to be, not total from the name and profeſſion of Chriſt ad of his Church, but a defection in the Church, an apoſtaſie from the purity of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, worſhip, Diſcipline and practice of the Goſpel, ſuch as ſhould have ſo many excuſes and ſpecious pretences for it, that the deluſion ſhould be ſtrong, and ſuch as thoſe that do not heartily love the truth, ſhould not be able to diſcern.</p>
            <p>Whence we collect this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,<note place="margin">Propoſition.</note> That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is and for a long time hath been the ſeat of this man of ſin, the mother of this apoſtaſie: or, That Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery is the grand Apoſtaſie of the Church here foretold. This I ſhall make good, firſt by ſome general reaſons, and then by the particular <hi>criteria,</hi> or marks laid down in the text.</p>
            <p>By the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> we mean all thoſe Nations and Churches which as ſo many members make up that great body which they call the Roman Catholick Church, whereof the Pope is the Head, and the Church of the City of <hi>Rome</hi> the principal part. By Popery we underſtand that religion, <hi>viz.</hi> Doctrines, worſhip, Diſcipline and Government, which is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40317:15"/>to them and diſtinct from all other Chriſtians, eſpecially from the Proteſtant Churches; and whereby they are knit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one body and ſociety, and live in one Communion diſtinct from and oppoſite to the Reformed Churches. Now that this Church is apoſtatized from Chriſt, and this religion is a Doctrine and practice of apoſtaſie, may appear in the general by comparing the true ſtate of the Church of Chriſt with the ſtate and Doctrine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, The true Church of Chriſt acknowledgeth and worſhippeth one only God; the creator of the world, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. This is the foundation of religion, that there is one only infinite Being, the fountain and author of all things elſe; and therefore that all worſhip, fear, truſt, and obedience is due to him alone, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Though there be that are called Gods, whether in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or in earth (as there are Gods many and Lords many) But to us there is but one God the Father, of whom are all things, and we in Him.</hi> But the Papiſts do acknowledge and worſhip other Gods beſides him, even the Hoſt or Bread in the Sacrament, and the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:40317:15"/>
            <p>The Heathens pretend to acknowledge but one ſupreme God: but the Papiſts do acknowledge that which ſenſe, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and ſcripture witneſs to be a bit of bread, to be the ſupreme God their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and Lord; which they uſually call the Hoſt; and that it is to be worſhipped <hi>cultu Latriae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conc. Trid. Seſ.</hi> 13. Cap. 4, 5. ibid. c. 6.</note> with that worſhip that is due to God alone: This they keep upon their Altar in a gilded Box in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Ark of old, there (they teach) is the ſpecial preſence of God, as it was in the Holy of Holies. This they worſhip, and carry in triumph, by this they ſwear, <hi>viz.</hi> by the Maſs, and by the Pix; and this is a peculiar note and badge of their communion, by which they diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence themſelves from others, and deſtroy all that do not acknowledge and worſhip this their God as far as their power reaches. The Hoſt hath its Temples, its Holydays, and all divine honours given to it, alſo the power of healing diſeaſes, caſting out Devils, and working all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of miracles aſcribed to it. The Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary</hi> hath more temples, offerings, and prayers made to her, than either the Father or the Son: Her name is moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred in oaths, and a greater offence it is to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40317:16"/>ſpeak any thing derogatory to her honour,<note place="margin">Vid. ſpec. Europ. <hi>Sands.</hi> Jure ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris impera re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempotri.</note> than to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the name of God. In her they put their truſt, and to her they aſcribe authority over Jeſus Chriſt himſelf. It is true, in words the Schoolmen diſtinguiſh the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Virgin which they call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from {fo}, the worſhip of God; yet they confeſs a higher worſhip is due to her than to any creature: and when we can make a medium betwixt the creator and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, then may we aſſign a worſhip which is not divine, and yet ſuperiour to the civil reſpect due to creatures.</p>
            <p>But the ſame learned author obſerves, that whoſoever travelleth in <hi>Italy</hi> will ſee in their practice no ſuch diſtinctions; but that more honour and worſhip is given to the Virgin than to God himſelf. It is known to all, that Papiſts are more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the worſhip of the Hoſt and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin (whom they call their Lady) than for the honour of God; and make the worſhip of them a greater cognizance of their religion than any part of the religion of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Churchof Chriſt acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and truſteth in one only Mediator the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. None can reconcile ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40317:16"/>to God nor intercede with God for them, but he that is equal with God, God himſelf; no creature can approach ſo near the infinite Majeſty, or have any, much leſs ſuch authority with him; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the divine honour that is given to Chriſt the Mediator doth not derogate from the honour of God, nor is any rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery of him, becauſe Chriſt is one with himſelf, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. There is but one Lord Jeſus Chriſt by whom are all things, and we by him. But the Papiſts do own, truſt in, and pray to many Mediators be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Jeſus Chriſt, even all the Angels in heaven, who are therefore to be honoured and worſhipped as inferiour Magiſtrates un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a King and Courtiers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Lord,<note place="margin">Catech. Rom. in <hi>1.</hi> praec. Q <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Noſtras preces deo offerunt &amp; Lachrymas,</hi> They preſent our prayers and tears to God. Alſo the Saints in heaven who, they ſay, being prayed to, will obtain for us the remiſſion of our ſins, and the favour of God. <hi>Si enim gaudium eſt in Coelo ſuper uno peccatore poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam agente;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. Q. 5.</note> 
               <hi>nonne etiam coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtes cives poenitentes adjuvabunt? Nonne rogati &amp; peccatorum veniam impetrabunt &amp; conciliabunt dei gratiam?</hi> The invocation and worſhip of Saints, as both lawful and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40317:17"/>is avouched and decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seſ. <hi>25.</hi> Decr. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Nor will their evaſion excuſe them, that they make Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels only mediators of interceſſion to pray to God for us, but not of redemption to reconcile us to God; interceſſion depends upon redemption and ſatisfaction, and is as proper a part of the prieſthood of Chriſt as the ſacrificeof himſelf was; even Chriſts interceſſion would not have been prevalent unleſs he did thereby preſent his blood and merits to the Fathers; and as the Saints couldnot intercede for us unleſs they had merited for us, ſo the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth aſcribe ſuch merits to them, <hi>viz.</hi> to their works of ſuperero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, whereby they have done more than God required, which merits they ſay are kept in the treaſury of the Church to be applied to ſinners as the Pope feeth fit, and eſpecially to their Martyrdom, though they die for rebellion to their lawful Princes, according to that known prayer, <hi>Per Thomae ſanguinem quem pro te impendit, fac nos Chriſte ſcandere quo Thomas aſcendit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Tho. Beck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et <hi>of</hi> Cant.</note> Grant that we may come to Heaven through the blood of Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> which he ſhed for thee. It is the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40317:17"/>merits and prayers of Saints that muſt relieve the ſouls in Purgatory,<note place="margin">Concil. Trid. ſeſ. <hi>25.</hi> decr. <hi>1. ibid.</hi> dec. <hi>22, 23. ch. 1.</hi>
               </note> yea every Maſs-prieſt, they ſay, cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating Maſs doth offer up Chriſt to the Father as real and proper a ſacrifice as he offered himſelf on the Croſs, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by makes reconciliation both for the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and dead, <hi>viz.</hi> that are in Purgatory. If then Chriſt was a compleat Prieſt, merited and ſatisfied for us in ſacrificing himſelf, then every Popiſh Prieſt doth me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and ſatisfy for us, when he offereth the ſame ſacrifice as Chriſt did to the ſame intent and purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Church of Chriſt is to worſhip him with ſpiritual, rational worſhip. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are to give themſelves to God as a living and the only acceptable ſacrifice, which is their reaſonable ſervice, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. and to worſhip Godin ſpirit and truth, in oppoſition both to the ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Heathen, and the ceremonies, and bodily worſhip of the <hi>Jews,</hi> in any place convenient for that purpoſe, <hi>John</hi> 4.22, 23, 24. The outward worſhip of Chriſtians conſiſteth in prayer and praiſes with underſtanding; ſometimes adjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faſting for the furtherance of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and mortification: in hearing Gods
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40317:18"/>word, and the reverent uſe of his ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which Chriſt hath appointed, which though they are outward and viſible ſigns, yet they are but few, plain, and familiar, and the efficacy of them dependeth upon the rational and ſpiritual conſideration of the things ſignified. But the Papiſts have changed the whole worſhip of God into a pompous, carnal, dead ſervice. They have taken away the Scriptures from the people, and give them dumb images in ſtead of them,<note place="margin">Con. Trid. Seſ. <hi>25.</hi> Dec. 3. Cat. Rom. in <hi>1.</hi> praecep. Q. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> to teach them and to excite their devotion. Inſtead of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the word, moſt of their preaching is to ſet out the praiſes and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miracles of their Saints. Their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers both publick and private are in a tongue unknown to the people and very often to the Prieſt alſo, who only reads by roat: and hereby prayer is made but a bodily exerciſe. When the Jeſuites had publiſhed an Engliſh prayer book for our Engliſh Papiſts, the Pope called it in and prohibited the uſe of it. There Lords ſupper they have changed to a ſacrifice (which the Prieſt offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with many myſtical, but ridiulous, ceremonies and geſtures) which they ſay obtains the pardon of ſin and the grace of God for the people for whom it is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40317:18"/>offered, though they underſtand not what is ſaidor done, yea though they be abſent, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing their worldly buſineſs, or their luſt at the ſame time. They darkne the nature &amp; meaning of baptiſm by conjuring the water, putting milk and honey into the mouth, ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle into the ears and on the tongues, anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the head, uſing ſalt &amp; many ſuch things, which being all in Latin not underſtood by the people are more like magical myſteries than Goſpel inſtitutions. Their chief wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip &amp; devotion lyeth in building and adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Temples, for Maſſes, not for preaching; in buying Maſſes, in decking of images with Gold, Jewels; in offering incenſe, and wax Candles; in pilgrimages, and offerings to their Saints; in vows of forced and uſually feigned chaſtity, &amp; of Hypocritical and lazy poverty, and ſuch like bodily exerciſes which profit little, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Church of Chriſt owneth him only for her head, King, and Lord. God gave Chriſt to be head over all things to his Church which is his body, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.23. He hath all power in Heaven and earth committed to him to rule and order all things concerning his Church which is his own houſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he appointed Apoſtles to bring all nations to be his Diſciples, to conſecrate
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40317:19"/>and ingage them to him by Baptiſm, and to teach them to obſerve all as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. Chriſt as mediator is the only head of the Church, which is his body, and all Chriſtians members in particular of him, receiving life, ſtrength, and ſpirit from him, and being governed by him. But the Papiſts acknowledge and adhere to the Pope as the head of their Church, which they ſay, could not be one Church unleſs it be united to the Pope as their viſible head.<note place="margin">Catec. Rom. de Symb. Art. <hi>9.</hi> Q. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>De eo, i. e. Pontifice Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano fuit illa omnium Patrum ratio &amp; ſententia conſentiens, hoc viſibiel caput ad unitatem eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae conſtituendam &amp; conſervandam neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um fuiſſe.</hi> They ſay that Chriſt and the Pope make but one compleat Head of the Church; That all which is ſaid in the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> or elſewhere concerning Chriſt's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to his Church may be truly apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Pope. That he hath all power in heaven and earth given to him.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. declared that it was abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man to be ſubject to the Pope of <hi>Rome: Definimus, decernimus, declaramus eſſe de neceſſitate ſalutis omni humanae creaturae eſſe ſubditum Pontifici Romano;</hi> accordingly they teach, <hi>peccatum pagantiatis incurrit quiſquis Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifici
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40317:19"/>non eſt obediens,</hi> i. e. Whoſoever is not obedient to the Pope doth thereby become an Heathen. They aſcribe to the Pope an univerſal headſhip not of order only, but of power and juriſdiction: he is the Rock, the foundation of the Church, he giveth authority to the Scriptures, and without him <hi>authoritas Scripturarum plane nulla eſt,</hi> ſaith one, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Scriptures have no authority at all: he can lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Bible if he pleaſe, or diſpenſe with any of the commands of the old or new Teſtament ſaith their Canon Law, and he daily doth diſpenſe with oaths, vows, and obligations of all ſorts, both to God and man, with unlawful marriages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They ſay indeed in diſputation that the Pope is a miniſterial head, the Deputy, the Vicar of Chriſt; but a Miniſter is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to execute the pleaſure of his Lord; a Deputy and Vicar is to ſee his Maſters laws and commands obſerved, not to enact laws of his own, not to relax or abrogate any of his Maſters laws, which power the Pope both challengeth and exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Chriſt's Church profeſſeth ſubjection to his law only, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.22. <hi>The Lord is our Judge, the Lord is our Law-giver, the Lord is our King.</hi> Chriſt is the only
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40317:20"/>King of his Church; and the power of making Laws is the chief prerogative of a King. He gave his word to be the ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Law, whereby his people ſhould be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and guided, and by which they muſt be judged at the laſt day, <hi>John</hi> 12.48. But the Papiſts have another Law, by which they are governed, and the Pope is their law-giver who ruleth them. The Scriptures they own indeed as the word of God, but not as his whole mind and law, and that no otherwiſe than as the Pope interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and alloweth them. They joyn with the Scriptures unwritten Traditions, which the Council of <hi>Tent</hi> ſaith are of equal authority. <hi>Traditiones non ſcriptas pari pietatis affectu &amp; reverentiâ ſuſcipit &amp; veneratur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conc. Trid. Seſ. <hi>4.</hi> Cat. Rom. Pref. Q. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> The Canons of Councils, <hi>viz.</hi> thoſe that the Pope likes and confirms, and the decretal Epiſtles of Popes they reckon equal with the Holy Scriptures. <hi>Decretales epiſtolae meritò inter Scripturas cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicas recenſentur.</hi> The conſciences of men they do ſubject to the determinations and commands of the Pope as to Jeſus Chriſt, ſo that the law of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is compoſed and made up of the Scriptures, Traditions, Canons and decretals of Popes, over all which the Pope ſuperintends as
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40317:20"/>the ſupreme law-giver to confirm, relax, add or alter as he pleaſeth, according to the known Ruleof Cardinal <hi>Cuſanus, Lex currit cum praxi &amp;c.</hi> Whatſoever is the preſent allowed practice of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that muſt be taken for the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible rule or law of Chriſt. So that the will of the Pope is the ſupreme law of conſcience to the Papiſt in this world.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Chriſts Church acknowledgeth only his Sacraments, Baptiſm and the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. The Sacraments of the Goſpel are badges of our profeſſed Subjection to Chriſt and of our dependance on him for remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſins, for grace and eternal life, and it is fit that Chriſt alone ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point what ſhould be the ſigns, Seals, and conveyances of his grace and the marks of ſubjection to him, and the tokens of the Covenant betwixt him and his people. Chriſt appointed his Diſciples to enter into his Covenant by the ſign and Seal of Baptiſm, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. to renew and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this Covenant from time to time by the uſe of his holy ſupper, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23, 24. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and he appointed no other but theſe: and his people muſt inſtitute and uſe no other as ſigns and Covenant ſeals betwixt him and them. But the Papiſts have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded five more, which they own and maintain
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40317:21"/>to be Sacraments, beſides many other ſignificant ceremonies to which they attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the uſe and effects of Sacraments, theſe they make ſigns of Gods Covenant, means to convey grace; ſome of them as univerſally neceſſary as thoſe that Chriſt appointed, yea without which Chriſts Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments are not ſufficient to Salvation, <hi>viz.</hi> the Sacraments of Confirmation and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; of the former they ſay, a man cannot be a Chriſtian till he be confirmed by the Biſhop, Baptiſm is not compleat without it.<note place="margin">De conſecra. diſt. <hi>5. ch.</hi> de jejun.</note> 
               <hi>Nemo poteſt eſſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus niſi ad Baptiſmum ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſerit unctio epiſcopalis, niſi confirmatione chriſmatus.</hi> Their penance conſiſteth of confeſſion of ſin to the Prieſt, contrition for ſin and the Prieſts abſolution; and they teach that ſins cannot be forgiven unleſs they be particularly confeſſed to the Prieſt, and he abſolve them in the name of Chriſt upon their undergoing or promiſe to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo ſome outward auſterity or penance impoſed on them by him. Theſe Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are badges and means of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the Prieſt and to the Pope their head, not to Chriſt. The Lords ſupper is not ſufficient to comfort a dying Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, but they add their Sacrament of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40317:21"/>unction to ſtrengthen them againſt the flames of Purgatory. Thus they have more Sacraments and for other ends than Chriſt appointed.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Chriſts Church is to be guided and governed only by the officers and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of his own appointing; and that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his word. Chriſt as the head and Saviour of his Church, hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that it ſhall be inſtructed and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his laws; guided and ruled by his officers in the practice and execution of his laws and Commands: what they ſhall be, he hath appointed, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12, to 16. <hi>viz.</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Prophets, &amp; Evangeliſts to convert the world: and raiſe his Church at firſt, Paſtors and Teachers to guide and inſtruct it to the end of the world, and theſe he hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to teach his people his Commands, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.20. to preach his word, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter his Sacraments, and to be examples to the flock of all humility and holineſs not for filthy lucre but out of deſire of their good, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1. <hi>to</hi> 4. But the Papiſts have quite altered the nature and uſe of the Miniſtry of the Church.<note place="margin">Council. Triden. Seſſ. <hi>23. ch. 1, 2, 3.</hi> Can. <hi>1, 2.</hi>
               </note> They have added five or ſix orders of Officers to thoſe that Chriſt appointed only for pomp and ſuperſtition, <hi>viz.</hi> Subdeacons, Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſts,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40317:22"/>Readers, Singers, Acolothites, and Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Their Prieſts preach not the word, but are chiefly ordained to offer the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſs, which alſo is moſt of their imployment. The Pope the Head of their Church is an earthly Monarch above all Princes and Emperors, living in all the ſtate and pomp of the old Roman Emperours, challenging the ſame honour &amp; obſervance, and more than they did (<hi>viz.</hi> the kiſſing of his feet) except one or two moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent Tyrants. His Cardinals are Princes, and the chief Cardinal Biſhop taketh place of the Emperours Embaſſadour, and the next takes place of all other Embaſſadours. Their whole miniſtry almoſt conſiſteth in hearing confeſſions, pardoning ſins, enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing penance, preaching the authority of the Pope, the Canons and Traditions of their own Church, and in ſaying Maſſes and prayers for the abſent and for the dead.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The great deſign of the Goſpel is, that men being reconciled to God may live to him in all holineſs and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and this is the practice of the Church of Chriſt. The Church is redeemed and purchaſed to be a peculiar people to Chriſt zealous of good works; therefore is it cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of the world, inſpired with his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40317:22"/>of grace and holineſs; taught by his holy law; and ſubjected to his holy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline; the work of Chriſtians is to be dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the world, mortifying their luſt, and growing in grace, in hope of and prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Glory, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.11, 12, 13, 14. But the deſign of Popery by keeping the people ignorant of the word and Sacraments is to bring them into ſubjection to the Pope and his Clergy.</p>
            <p>Their ordinances and worſhip tend not to purifie the conſcience, but under a vain ſhew of a carnal pompous ſervice to cheat them of knowledge and ſpiritual edification, and to enthral men to their Church and their own Inſtitutions. They teach that the bare uſe of the Sacraments confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth grace, though a man neither under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what he doth, nor is ſerious in it: and if perhaps he ſhould be ſerious, yet the efficacy of the Sacraments dependeth on the Prieſts intention; ſo that if he be not ſerious or underſtandeth not what he doth, the Communicant can have no benefit. They tolerate all manner of wickedneſs. Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> teacheth, it is better for their Clergy to live in ſecret fornication than to marry, <hi>Satius eſt pluribus occultis impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari, quam in conſpectu mundi cum una ligari.</hi> And the people may live how they pleaſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40317:23"/>ſo they be obedient to the orders of the Church, confeſs, and receive Maſs once a year, this will blot out all ſin; and though a man ſhould live in wickedneſs all his days, yet if he but die in their communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with the Prieſts abſolution, which may be eaſily had, he ſhall go to Purgatory but for a time and ſo to Heaven: and money may procure Maſſes and prayers for him when dead, that will haſten his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance thence alſo; ſo that they that will not leave their ſins while they live, may buy their pardon and redemption from torment after they are dead: how can there be a more effectual way to encourage men in ſin?</p>
            <p n="9">9. Self-denyal, contempt of the world, and bearing the Croſs are the profeſſion and badge of Chriſts Church. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour declared that his Kingdom was not of this world: and his Diſciples muſt not expect, nor fight for it here, <hi>John</hi> 18.36. He hath promiſed them his ſpirit and comforts in a greater meaſure than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, becauſe they were to meet with much tribulation in this world, <hi>John</hi> 16.33. and our Saviour hath given us this univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal rule, except a man deny himſelf and take up his croſs and follow me, he cannot be my Diſciple, <hi>Lub.</hi> 14.27. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.24. But the Papiſts make outward proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40317:23"/>and grandeur a mark of the true Church; and that the Pope and Biſhops are Princes above all Princes, and that inſtead of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any perſecution they are to make War upon all Princes that diſpleaſe them, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy by open force of battle or ſudden Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacres, and private treacheries all they can reach that are not obedient to them, or ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected not to be hearty, or but to favour or be mild towards thoſe they call Hereticks.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Heaven is propoſed as the certain reward of the ſervants of Chriſt. The grace of God that brings Salvation teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us to deny all ungodlineſs and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly and godlily in this world, looking for the glorious appearance of God our Saviour, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13. In this life Chriſtians are to fight, ſtrive and run, but when this life ends, their courſe is finiſhed, and there remains nothing but a Crown of life which the righteous judge ſhall give to all them that love his appearance, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6, 7. But the Papiſts teach that all aſſurance of Salvation is preſumption;<note place="margin">Concil. Triden. Seſ. <hi>6. ch. 12, 13.</hi> Can. <hi>15, 16.</hi>
               </note> the moſt we muſt expect is after many af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions from Gods hand and voluntary ſeverities upon our ſelves to ſatisfie for ſin, at laſt to go to Purgatory for a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40317:24"/>long time there to ſuffer the ſame torments that the damned do in Hell. It is reported of <hi>Bellarmin</hi> that when ſome about him would have comforted him at his death with his great merits, and that he ſhould certainly go to heaven; he anſwered, It is not ſo eaſie a thing to get to heaven, and that he could be content to ſuffer the pains of Purgatory many years if he could be ſure to come to heaven at laſt. Thus though they tell men they may merit Heaven and do works of ſupererogation, <hi>viz.</hi> more than God requires of them, yet they muſt go through Purgatory: hereby rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing them of the comfort of the Goſpel, and miſerably enthralling their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences to themſelves and their Tradition.</p>
            <p>By all this it is evident that the Papiſts have altered the nature and ends of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an religion, which was the doctrine and inſtitution of Jeſus Chriſt to exalt him as the only mediator of the Church by whom only we ſhould come to God, and have fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a new platform of a carnal worldly religion, to exalt the Pope and his Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and to worſhip the creatures inſtead of the Creatour. Let us add their doctrine of perſecuting and deſtroying all Hereticks (as they call them, that is, all that will not obey them) The firſt Lateran Council,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40317:24"/>
               <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 1215. decreeth,<note place="margin">Sub Innoc. <hi>3.</hi> P.</note> That if any Prince or Lord be a Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick or favourer of Hereticks, or will not deſtroy his own ſubjects being Hereticks, he ſhall be deprived of his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and it be given to ſome other Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prince. Accordingly they gave away the Eſtates of divers Earls, <hi>Ramund</hi> Earl of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Beſieres</hi> and others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the former favoured, the other would not deſtroy the <hi>Albigenſes</hi> their Subjects.<note place="margin">Vid. Hiſt. Walden.</note> The Inquiſition giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth orders not only to deſtroy Hereticks, but alſo all ſuch as favour them or habour them, or give them any relief in their diſtreſs, or conceal them or any of their goods; Yea that thoſe, who do not diſcover and accuſe their own relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or friends being Hereticks ſhall them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves be puniſhed as Hereticks.<note place="margin">In Concil. Conſtan.</note> Pope <hi>Martin</hi> the 5. decreed by a Bull, That Hereticks ſhould not be ſuffered to buy or ſell, or to injoy the benefit of humane ſociety. This Doctrine and their practice according to it makes them an Apoſtatical body or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, maintaining it ſelf in oppoſition to the pure Church of Chriſt, and therefore to take part with them, to joyn with or ſubmit to their intereſt, is to deſert Chriſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40317:25"/>and to ſide with or become a member of that great Apoſtaſie.</p>
            <p>Let us now take notice of the ſeveral characters or marks that the Apoſtle gives of this Apoſtaſie, which will further prove the Papiſts to be guilty of it. The firſt is <hi>v.</hi> 3. That the Head of it is the man of ſin, the ſon of perdition, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. An Hebraiſm, where the genitive of the ſubſtantive is put for the adjective, and that by way of eminency, The ſinful or wicked man, as he is afterward called, <hi>v.</hi> 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the wicked or lawleſs man; <hi>v.</hi> 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſon of perdition, this is exegetical of the former, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch a wicked man as is ripe for and appointed to deſtruction. By this is meant not a particular perſon, but a ſtate or govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the hands of one or more perſons, though perhaps ſome one of thoſe gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors may be intended in a ſpecial manner as more ſingularly wicked and active than others, even as <hi>Nebuchadnezzer</hi> was ſaid to be the head of Gold of the great image,<note place="margin">Dan. 2.</note> 
               <hi>i. e.</hi> in ſpecial manner, though the whole ſeries of the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> and <hi>Babylonian</hi> Monarchs for 1300. years was repreſented thereby. Thus the Devil is expreſſed ſingularly when the whole ſociety of thoſe wicked ſpirits is intended, and no
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40317:25"/>one particular meant. And the four Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies are expreſſed by 4.<note place="margin">Dan. 7.</note> Beaſts though they were poſſeſſed not only by many Kings, but the laſt by the people of <hi>Rome</hi> for a long time, conſiſting of the Senate and <hi>Plebeian.</hi> The Papiſts would infer from theſe notes of particularity that Antichriſt this man of ſin muſt be but one particular perſon,<note place="margin">Vid. Whit. reſp. ad. Sand. Q. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and therefore not the Popes who have been many.</p>
            <p>But themſelves grant, what is here ſaid, <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>He that letteth will let till he be taken out of the way,</hi> is meant of the Roman Empire which was in the hand of many ſucceſſively, though expreſſed as one man: and it is common ſo to expreſs States or Kingdoms when we ſpeak of their conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, prerogatives or Laws. And when our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.18, 19. ſaid to <hi>Simon, Thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my Church, and I will give thee the Keys of the Kingdom, &amp;c.</hi> they will needs have it meant that this was granted to <hi>Peter</hi> and all his ſucceſſours the Popes, though none but <hi>Peters</hi> name is mentioned. Why then may we not ſo underſtand the man of ſin here? The Apoſtles ſenſe is, there well come an apoſtaſie of the Church,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40317:26"/>a declining in and from religion, which will encreaſe till the man of ſin be reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>i.e.</hi> till theſe apoſtates ſhall frame them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a body and ſtate of a moſt wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed government: this is the Pope and his Clergy, who ſucceſſively govern and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage that Apoſtaſie. This will appear if we conſider the wickedneſs of their Perſons, Doctrines and Practices.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For their perſons. There was a ſeries of Popes for about an hundred years in the 10. and 11. Centuries who were Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians, Murderers, open Adulterers and deſtroyers of each other; of whom <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brard</hi> the Jeſuite ſaith they were <hi>Apoſtatici potius quam Apoſtolici,</hi> apoſtates rather than Apoſtolical men. <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7. they report poyſoned 6 Popes his Predeceſſours to obtain the Papacy, and was himſelf a known Magician, he threw the hoſt his breaden God into the fire, becauſe it would not anſwer him in his Magical charms. Many others of them have been profeſſed Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians, ſome bold Atheiſts, as <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. who ſaid to Cardinal <hi>Bembus,</hi> Behold what great riches we get by that fable of Chriſt, <hi>Quantas opes nobis tulit iſta fabula de Chriſto.</hi> Moſt Adulterous <hi>Sodomites, Simoniacks,</hi> and ſome have lived in inceſt with their own Siſters and daughters: inſomuch that one
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40317:26"/>of themſelves gives this teſtimony, <hi>Nemo hodie in Pentificibus Romanis vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem aut pietatem requirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Invita Pauli tertii.</note> opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi putantur ſi vel mediocriter boni ſint, vel minus mali quam caeteri mortalium eſſe ſolent. i.e.} No man looks for virtue or godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs nowadays in the Popes, they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted moſt excellent if they be but indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently good, or not quite ſo bad as other men.</p>
            <p>The Cardinals and all their Clergy are like their head and father, being allowed <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domy,</hi> fornication, and adultery to keep them chaſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> from marrying. Where ſhall we find a man of ſin if this be not him?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Next conſider we their wicked do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That of abſolute ſubjection to the Pope, that whatſoever he commandeth muſt be done though never ſo wicked. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Etiamſi Papa erraret pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibendo virtutem &amp; praecipiendo vitium, &amp;c.</hi> Though the Pope ſhould forbid virtue and command vice he muſt be obeyed; And their law ſaith, <hi>ſi Papa totos populos ſecum in inſernum traheret, nemo poteſt ei dicere, Domine cur ita facis. i. e.</hi> Though the Pope ſhould draw whole Nations into Hell with himſelf, yet none may ſay to him why doſt thou ſo. This daily experience atteſteth.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40317:27"/>Murdering of Kings, deſtroying of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, any villanies muſt be done and that upon pain of damnation, if the Pope or any inferiour governour of their Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy commands it. Never any ſtate or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the world (though many have been very wicked) challenged this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative to command whatſoever they plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, right or wrong, and that men are bound in conſcience to obey them though againſt God and men, but this the Pope doth challenge and practiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Doctrine of the Popes infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, whereby they father all their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, ſuperſtitions, and corruptions upon the ſpirit of God. It is blaſphemous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God to imagine that he ſhould an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex the infallible guidance of his ſpirit to a ſucceſſion of men who defile and deſtroy his Church, oppoſe his ſon and his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and themſelves are Monſters of men. <hi>Innocent</hi> the 10.<note place="margin">S. Amore's Journ.</note> (who ſuffered himſelf and his holy Church to be governed by an impudent Harlot <hi>Don Olympia</hi> his own Brothers wife) when the people of <hi>Rome</hi> complained to him of the unjuſt exactions of his Officers anſwered them, You muſt not find fault which mine Officers, for I chuſe them and I am guided by the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40317:27"/>ſpirit of God. What is more wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than to aſcribe wicked actions to the guidance of Gods ſpirit? Some Papiſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed acknowledge not the Popes infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, but then they aſcribe it to a Council of Biſhops moſt of them as good and as wiſe as the Pope.</p>
            <p>Some give it to the whole Roman Church, but it will come all to one, if whatſoever the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> or the Heads and guides of it do determine, muſt be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed infallibly true and good, hereby they wholly wave the Scriptures as the Rule, and Chriſt as their Law-giver, and are both Rule and Law-givers to themſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Papiſts have reduced the whole body of the Heatheniſh worſhip into the Church: and this is the greateſt part of their worſhip. The Heathens honoured the good Angels with divine honours, as the ſervants of the ſupreme God, that they might be their friends to him, and that they might do them many good Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. They deified men and women emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in any way, eſpecially Princes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured them with Temples, Images, Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val days, and Sacrifices, that they might mediate with God for the good of their Country, family, or friends, putting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their affairs under their ſpecial
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40317:28"/>protection, and this took up moſt of their worſhip. The Papiſts do aſcribe the very ſame honour and worſhip in all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to the Angels and Saints, and for the ſame reaſons every Country, City, yea every perſon hath his Tutelar Saint, and upon theſe they call, and to theſe they pay more devotion by many degrees than they do to God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Their Caſuiſts allow common ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and uſing of the name of God lightly in common diſcourſe, and contend that the Third Commandment forbideth only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, ſwearing falſely or to a falſe thing in the name of God. Hence it is that Papiſts almoſt univerſally are common and profane ſwearers.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They teach that the Pope in all and the inferiour Clergy in ordinary caſes can diſpenſe with Oaths, Vows and the moſt ſolemn obligations that can be made to God or man. The Pope taketh himſelf for head of the Church, therefore what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever vows and ingagements men make to God, he can looſe them from them; when it ſerves his intereſt he gives licence to men and women to marry, who have vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſingle life, and to his Fryars to leave off the habit and rules of their order, though they have vowed never to lay them aſide.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40317:28"/>Alſo as he is Lord of all the world he can give away Kingdoms, looſe Subjects from their oaths of Allegiance, yea make it their duty to break their oaths and to rebel, and what is moſt abominable, they can give men leave to take Oaths, to make vowes and proteſtations on purpoſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, when they do not intend they ſhall be kept, but be uſed to carry on their own deſigns the more ſecretly by deceiving the credulous.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt. Albig.</hi> Book 1. ch. 5.</note> Thus the Popes Legat ſent a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman to the Earl of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiers</hi> to draw him into his Camp, commanding him to aſſure him in his name by what Oaths and proteſtations he would deſire, that he ſhould return ſafe home; as ſoon as the poor Earl came into his preſence he abſolved the meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from all his Oaths, kept the Earl pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner and ſoon after privately murdered him.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They make the Sabbath either a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or an inſtitution of their Church, profane it with ſports and plays, and obſerve their Saints days with much more ſtrictneſs and devotion than the Lords day.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Pope and his Clergy can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve all bonds and duties betwixt men.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40317:29"/>They can command Princes to deſtroy their Subjects, and abſolve them from all their oaths and promiſes to them of protection; They can diſcharge Subjects from their obedience to their Princes, and make it meritorious of heaven to kill them, and a ſure way to go to heaven immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to dye in fighting againſt them. They can divorce or ſeparate hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and Wives at their pleaſure.<note place="margin">Concil. Trid. Seſ. <hi>24.</hi> Canon. <hi>6.</hi> Can. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alphonſus</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King of <hi>Portugal</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and impriſoned by the Popes order, and his wife taken from him and given to his Brother two now rules the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Parents and children, Maſters and ſervants in caſe of Hereſie muſt betray each other; and if they will enter into religious houſes or give any thing to the Church, then they are freed from all obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations to, or care of their relations. Is not this a man of ſin that can and daily doth diſſolve all bonds of men to God and of men to themſelves?</p>
            <p n="8">8. They teach that no faith, leagues, promiſes are to be kept with Hereticks, or any that are not of their Church. Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> the 4 made <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Hungary</hi> break his league with the <hi>Turk</hi> ſolemnly ſworn by him and all his Nobles,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40317:29"/>and abſolved them by <hi>Julian</hi> his Legate. The Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> burnt <hi>John Huſs,</hi> though the Emperour <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him ſafe-conduct to and from the Council, they telling the Emperour that Oaths and promiſes to Hereticks muſt not be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="9">9. They teach Equivocations and mental reſervations both in oaths and common diſcourſes, <hi>viz.</hi> that a man may take any Oath, make any promiſe, anſwer any Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion directly and plainly according to the words propoſed, and yet mean no ſuch thing or the contrary, keeping another ſenſe or intent in their minds. <hi>Garnet</hi> and <hi>Treſmond</hi> two <hi>Jeſuites</hi> that were in the powder Plot being examined apart, <hi>Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> ſaid he had not ſeen or ſpoke with <hi>Garnet</hi> for 14. years before, <hi>Garnet</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that they two walked and diſcourſed together in <hi>Moorefields London</hi> about four months before they were taken: being asked what his fellow meant to ſay they had not met ſo long a time, he anſwered, I ſuppoſe he meant to equivocate, and this was excuſe enough. Thus all bonds of humane Society and all means of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and confidence in each other may be diſſolved when the Pope or a Prieſt pleaſeth. If any Papiſt pretend to diſown
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40317:30"/>any of theſe doctrines, I demand by what rule he doth it? By the Scripture? the Law of Nations? or the Law of nature? they all maintain the Pope is above theſe: Theſe are not a perfect rule neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part nor together, nor do reach all caſes; if they did, there were no need of an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible head to direct the Church, nor any warrant for moſt of the worſhip and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> If then the Pope be above all, and infallible, then a Papiſt muſt believe that in this and that particular caſe that concerns him he may and muſt break his Oaths, deny his promiſes, murder, lye, or commit any ſuch enormity when commanded, or elſe he prefers his own judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Popes and denies his principles. Whence we may ſee that no truſt is to be repoſed in a Papiſt, becauſe they are not maſters of their own reaſon and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, of their Oaths and promiſes, but the Pope and their Confeſſours have the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal of them all, and make them do as they pleaſe: and ſo long as their Church chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth a power and juriſdiction over all the world, and is always contending for it, it is to be ſuppoſed their rulers will always put them upon thoſe things that promote their own intereſt.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:40317:30"/>
            <p n="10">10. Their doctrines that extenuate ſin and make forgiveneſs very eaſiy, are nothing elſe but doctrines of wickedneſs. They extenuate ſin by their doctrine of venial ſins, which they ſay are <hi>praeter, non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Legem,</hi> not commanded by God nor forbidden of him, and therefore ſcarce to be called ſins.</p>
            <p>Such they make all firſt thoughts, and motions of the mind and affections to be, when there is not a deliberate aſſent with them; all wandering thoughts, diſtractions in holy duties, the ſtirrings of the moſt vile affections with ſome titillation or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing are all but natural actions and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities which do not deſerve Hell or the wrath of God.</p>
            <p>They make pardon of ſin very eaſie. Upon confeſſion to the Prieſt he doth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve upon ſome eaſie penance almoſt any ſin; and thoſe reſerved caſes, which the Prieſt cannot pardon, are forgiven by the Pope for money. There is a printed book called <hi>Taxa poenitentiariae Apoſtolicae,</hi> wherein the prices are ſet down for all manner of ſins: and in the general all ſins againſt God and his Law are more eaſily forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven than thoſe againſt the Popes law and Tradition. What need men fear to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin that can be ſo eaſily remitted, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40317:31"/>to them that have money? They have alſo another device of transferring their ſins upon their friends, <hi>viz.</hi> a few friends agree together to take each others ſins upon them, ſo that he who dieth firſt leaveth his ſins to be ſatisfied for by the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivours; and they again take others into their number, and ſo can ſin ſecurely, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Executors to pay their debts for them when they are dead. The Sacrifice of the Maſs offered for them by the Prieſt alone expiates all ſin, ſo that for 6 pence or 12 pence a Maſs, any ſins may be tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en away, though they be not preſent or concerned about it, or be committing wickedneſs the mean while.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Though a man live all his days in wickedneſs, if he die in the communion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and be abſolved by a Prieſt, which is rarely denyed to any, he muſt go but to Purgatory and there ſatisfie for all his ſins, and at laſt be ſaved: and if he leave any thing to the Church, or his friends will buy Maſſes or prayers for him, his time in Purgatory ſhall be ſhortened and his pains leſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Their Practice is as wicked as their doctrine, not that only of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, which is incident to all
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40317:31"/>ſocieties, but the allowed practice of the Church, and that whereby their State is upheld. To inſtance in a few.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They perſecute and by all means deſtroy all that ſubmit not to them in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing; ſo that in <hi>Rome</hi> is found the blood of all the Saints and Martyrs that have been ſlain in all the earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhed by her command. About the year 750. the Popes <hi>Gregory</hi> 2. and 3. begun wars againſt the Emperors and their adherents in the defence of Image wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and afterward renewed them to obtain the right of inveſtitures or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing of all Eccleſiaſtical preferments, and to deprive the Emperours of their power of electing the Pope, till they had brought the Emperours under their feet, and compelled all the Clergy to put away their Wives. Thus the Popes ruined all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom for about 400. years, till they had got all the power into their hands: and ever ſince they have ſhed blood in abundance to preſerve what they had gotten. They began with the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> about the year 1160. of whom <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uanus</hi> ſaith they had ſlain above two Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, and they have added many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands more of late years of that poor people. Afterward they deſtroyed
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40317:32"/>many thouſands in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> both in the former and late wars. <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerius</hi> who was the Popes Nuncio tells us that in the ſpace of 30. years at the firſt reſormation their inquiſition in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts had ſecretly made away 150000 perſons. The Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> Governour of the <hi>Neatherlands</hi> in a few years is ſaid to cut off 36000. The <hi>French</hi> Maſſacre <hi>Ann.</hi> 1572. in one Month treacherouſly and barbarouſly deſtroyed above 30000. In the late <hi>Iriſh</hi> rebellion <hi>Ann.</hi> 1641. they deſtroyed above 300000. of all ages and conditions: and what they have done and attempted and do ſtill attempt upon this Land is well known. All theſe were au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by the Popes, and had their bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and prayers for ſucceſs; beſides the innumerable company of Martyrs which they have put to death by form of tryals in all countreys.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their toleration of all uncleanneſs, beſides what they allow in their Clergy privately. They have publick Stews in all Cities of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and the Pope has a tribute from them for their Licences. Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 4. built at his own Charge a famous Stew in <hi>Rome</hi> both for men and women. <hi>Paul</hi> the 3. had Catalogues found amongſt his Papers after his death,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40317:32"/>of 45000. Strumpets, who payed him a monthly impoſition.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are allowed Simony, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of all Eccleſiaſtical offices. There is another book called <hi>Taxa cancalleriae apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicae</hi> i. e. of the Popes Chamber, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the prices of all benefices, and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are ſet down: no places of any value are diſpoſed of without money. A nameleſs Papiſt dedicated a book to King <hi>James</hi> wherein he acquaints him that all the Popes from <hi>Clement</hi> the 7.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Called</hi> the new man.</note> to his time had got the Popedom by Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and other indirect means. This he was able to prove: but he might truly have ſaid, ſo did all the reſt for many ages before. In <hi>England</hi> formerly benefices have been ſold to two, three, or more, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to ten ſeveral perſons, and then when the incumbent died, the Pope muſt be judge who ſhall have it of all theſe, which ſhall certainly be he that will give moſt money; Thus they make woful Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize with mens ſouls.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Continual endeavours to ſtir up wars and imbroil Nations. The Pope pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to be Lord of Lords and King of Kings: and therefore he diſpoſeth of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, ſets up and pulls down Princes as
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40317:33"/>he pleaſes, and this is a ſufficient pretence for any unjuſt wars and invaſions; and wherever there are any differences among Princes and their Subjects, he interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his authority, uſually taking the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt part (if like to prevail) that they being beholding to him may requite him with ſome addition to his authority or revenue. Pope <hi>Zacheriah</hi> gave <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Pipin</hi> an aſpiring man, depoſing <hi>Childerick</hi> their lawful King as unfit to govern. <hi>Leo</hi> the 4. gave the Empire of the Romans to <hi>Charles</hi> the great, and another gave <hi>England</hi> to the <hi>French</hi> in King <hi>Johns</hi> time, and ſent them to Conquer it: and of late the Pope gave the <hi>Eaſt Indies</hi> to the <hi>Portugal,</hi> and the Weſt to the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> where they murdred the poor natives as wild beaſts made to be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Theſe doctrines and practices are not taught and practiſed by a few only among them, but they are the State policies by which they ſtand, which they never diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own, never endeavour to reform: it is the deſign of their government to be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal and to attain it by any means.</p>
            <p>Hence we infer that to hold communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with this Church is to conſpire againſt the Church of Chriſt, againſt all that is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred or moral. Nor may we expect any
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:40317:33"/>reformation from them, they will not they cannot be better; their intereſt and government depends upon theſe methods, and therefore this Man of ſin is the ſon of perdition appointed to be deſtroyed, not to be reformed: let us not deceive our ſelves with vain hopes; They are and muſt be the ſame when they have opportunity.</p>
            <p>The ſecond character of this Apoſtaſie is laid down <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Who oppoſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, viz.</hi> the man of ſin the Head of this apoſtaſie. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an adverſary or one that ſets himſel againſt Chriſt. The ſame title that is given to the Devil, <hi>viz.</hi> Satan an enemy or adverſary. Now the Devil was an adverſary not by denying the true God; <hi>he believes and trembles, James</hi> 2.19. nor by cauſing himſelf to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped as the ſupreme God; for the Idols which the Heathens worſhipped, they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped as Mediators and ſervants to the ſupreme God; but under this pretence the Devil took to himſelf all the worſhip and ſervice of the world, and left God but an empty name of Creatour and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme reſiding in heaven, when he himſelf was the God of this world, ordering all things after his own luſts: this the Devil did ſo long as Heatheniſm prevailed, by the ſeveral Governours and Princes of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40317:34"/>the world, and when he was caſt out of Heaven, <hi>viz.</hi> his worſhip, <hi>Idolatry</hi> and Heatheniſh ſuperſtition aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the fail of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Roman Empire,<note place="margin">Rev. 12. <hi>v.</hi> 7, 8, 9, 10.</note> and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the name of Chriſt was taken away, he caſt about, and after ſome time delivered his power to the ſecond Beaſt who uſed the power and tyranny of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Beaſt; <hi>i. e.</hi> the Roman Empire op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Chriſt and his worſhip, ſetting up himſelf with all ſuperſtition and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> but under fair pretences of Chriſts autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This beaſt was like a Lamb, but ſpake as the Dragon, and uſed all the power of the former beaſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the Heathen government. Now that the Pope and his adherents do thus oppoſe Chriſt and not his name but his power and worſhip, drawing all ſubjection to himſelf and leaving Chriſt but a bare and empty title, he being as <hi>Stapleton</hi> calls him plain <hi>ſupremum in terris numen, i. e.</hi> the moſt high and abſolute God in earth,</p>
            <p>It is manifeſt,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Pope will not ſuffer Chriſt to be King and law-maker in his Church. Kingly power conſiſteth in making laws and ruling according to them; this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to Chriſt; and he gave his word to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40317:34"/>be the law of his Church, and his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to execute and adminiſter it according to his mind. But the Pope challengeth the ſole power and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church on earth to belong to him; the authority of the Scriptures to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him; that he can add to them, take from them, or diſpenſe with any thing there commanded; that he only muſt interpret and give them their ſenſe; that his determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations is the rule of conſcience, for whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he defineth or commandeth is to be believed and obeyed: and ſo under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Chriſts Vicar he rules as Chriſt on earth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Pope will not allow Chriſt to appoint the ordinances of his own wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. It belongs to Chriſt as King to appoint how and by whom he will be worſhipped, but the Pope will not give him leave. He appoints more orders of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers than Chriſt did; more Sacraments, and alters thoſe of his appointing; the bread in the ſupper he maketh a God to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, and yet a Sacrifice to be offered to God; the cup he takes away from the people, the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> moſt inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently telling us that though our Lord Chriſt inſtituted and gave his ſupper to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles under both kinds, of bread and wine,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40317:35"/>yet that doth not oblige all the faithful to receive it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both kinds.<note place="margin">Concil. Trid. Seſ. <hi>21. ch. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Etſi Chriſtus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus in ultima coena venerabile hoc Sacramentum in panis &amp; vini ſpecicbus inſtituit &amp; Apoſtlis tradidit: non tamen illa inſtitutio &amp; traditio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ò tendunt, ut omnes Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti fideles ſtatuto domini ad utramque ſpeciem accipiendam aſtringantur?</hi> He appoints Saints and Angels and eſpecially Chriſts Mother to be worſhipped and honoured, yea the very Croſs on which he was murdered, pretending theſe to be more honour to Chriſt than the preaching or hearing his holy word. Almoſt the whole body of the Papiſts worſhip is of the Popes own inſtitution.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Pope will not ſuffer Chriſt to appoint the means of his own grace to Salvation. Chriſt as the Saviour of his people, as divine and Princely Saviour is to appoint and hath appointed by what means and in what duties he will beſtow and increaſe his grace to eternal life: but the Pope lays theſe aſide at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, <hi>viz.</hi> the reading and hearing the Scripture, the uſe of the Sacraments, and prayer in a tongue that can be underſtood by thoſe that uſe it, and appointeth more upon which the greateſt ſtreſs of ſalvation is laid; as confeſſion of ſin to Prieſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40317:35"/>out which there is no forgiveneſs to the living; and private Maſſes both for the quick and dead; anointing of Children to confirm them in grace, and anointing the dying to ſtrengthen and comfort them againſt the terror of death; croſſes and holy water to drive away the devil; and ſo many of this kind that they have greatly obſcured the means of grace that Chriſt inſtituted.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Pope oppoſeth Chriſt in the main ends of his coming into the world. Chriſt came to take away ſin, to finiſh tranſgreſſion and to bring in everlaſting righteouſneſs by once ſacrificing himſelf to the Father, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.10, 11, 12, 13, 14. But the Pope will have Chriſt offered for ſin in every Maſs, as truly as he was upon the Croſs; and that it is as ſatisfactory and meritorious; he will have the merits of Saints, our own penance, and purgatory oſter death to ſatisfy for and take away ſin, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſatisfaction of Chriſt is rendered as ſtill unfulfilled and the pardon of ſin unprocured as it was before his coming into the world. Chriſt came to give a greater meaſure of his ſpirit to the Church, that his people might have more freedom of acceſs to God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.12. more boldneſs with him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19, 20. and more
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40317:36"/>abundant grace to enable them to pray to and ſerve God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.25. <hi>John</hi> 10.10. for having removed the ſhadows and ſacrifices of the Law, and clearly exhibited himſelf and his redemption, they were now to come with greater confidence and freedom through his name to the Father, <hi>John</hi> 16.23, 24. but the Pope diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all this by hiding from the people the plain doctrine of ſalvation, by teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them that they muſt not come to him immediately but by the mediation of his Mother and all the Saints, and that theſe muſt be ingaged by many prayers, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and offerings to interceed with Chriſt for them, whereby the ſervice of the Goſpel is made as uncomfortable and as chargable as that of the Law; and the people are kept in as much ignorance as ever the <hi>Jews</hi> were, and in as much bondage to their Prieſts and more, without whoſe Maſſes and abſolutions they cannot be forgiven: yea by their doctrines and uncertainty of Salvation, penances, ſatisfactions, and purgatory, and the neceſſity of Chriſt's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing often ſacrificed for them, their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are brought into a far greater bondage than ever the <hi>Jews</hi> were in. Again Chriſt by his death, reſurrection and aſcenſion hath obtained all power, conquered the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:40317:36"/>Devil, opened a clear way into heaven for his ſervants, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.9, 10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.19, 20, 29. But the Papiſts keep the people in as great bondage by fear of the Devil as ever the Heathens were in: except there be a Croſs in the way they are in danger to meet him at every turning, in every Church-yard, Market, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea every time they go out of doors unleſs they croſs themſelves, or be ſprinkled with holy water: if it were not for croſſes the devil would get into their meat, their drink, their books, their beds, and into their pockets alſo. And as for Chriſts entering into Heaven it is little comfort to them, ſeeing they muſt hope to go thither but after ſome thouſands of years ſpent in the pains of Purgatory.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Chriſt aboliſhed the Tyranny and bondage his people were in both to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Monarchs and the Jewiſh Polity. Chriſt appeared in the latter end of the fourth Monarchy to ſet up his Kingdom, that his people might be ſubject to him, and no longer to the luſts and wills of lawleſs Tyrants as they had ſucceſſively been oppreſſed and devoured both by <hi>Babylonians, Perſians, Greeks,</hi> and <hi>Romans:</hi> and he promiſed that Kings ſhould be their nurſing fathers and Queens nurſing
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40317:37"/>mothers, being ſubject as well as they to the laws of Chriſt. But the Pope inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth and uſurpeth all the domination and prerogatives, and exerciſeth all the Tyranny of the Roman Emperours, cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all people to ſubmit to <hi>Rome</hi> with as great ſlavery as ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 15, 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and maketh laws as abſolutely by his own will as ever the Heathens did. Chriſt alſo diſſolved the Jewiſh Polity that his people ſhould no longer be bound to one temple, City or Land for any part of their worſhip as the <hi>Jews</hi> were to <hi>Canaan</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> or to any Common wealth of People: but that in all places they might lift up pure hands to him, and have his preſence with them whereever two or three ſhould be gathered in his name for the intents or purpoſes of his worſhip, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.19, 20. But the Pope will have <hi>Rome</hi> to be the mother of all the Churches, thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the world muſt come to keep their Jubilees every five and twenty years, thither they muſt bring their controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and hard caſes; and many ſins can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be forgiven without coming to him as the high Prieſt: all Churches depend upon him, yea are one body whereof he is the Head, and muſt receive their laws, their Prieſts, their benedictions all from
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40317:37"/>him and his power: ſo that they are in greater bondage than the <hi>Jews</hi> were, by how much they are diſperſed abroad in the world, and are more numerous.</p>
            <p>A third character of this Apoſtaſie is inſolent pride, <hi>v.</hi> 4. This man of ſin and adverſary of Chriſt exalteth himſelf above all that is worſhipped or called God, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or as <hi>Calvin</hi> in <hi>loc.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he is lifted up above all that is called God, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or that is any way ſacred. We read of ſome Heathen Princes, as <hi>Romulus, Alexander, &amp;c.</hi> that would be accounted the ſons of God and be worſhipped, but their own people deteſted their pride, and yet they acknowledged a ſupreme God above them. <hi>Caligula</hi> would be thought equal with <hi>Jupiter</hi> their chief God: but theſe were impious inſolencies never eſtabliſhed by laws, or approved by the people, much leſs defended and practiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſucceeding generations: but this Popes arrogate to themſelves through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ages ſucceſſively: this their whole Clergy defend and their whole people practiſe: yea it is the very ſoul and life of the Popedom to be honoured and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above all that is called God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Magiſtrates are called Gods, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40317:38"/>Gods Vicegerents, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 82.6. But the Pope exalteth himſelf above all theſe, challenging the dominion of the whole world to be given to him; and he diſpoſeth of it to whom he pleaſeth: He calleth Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and Kings his ſervants and vaſſals: He ſets them up and pulls them down at his pleaſure. <hi>Paul</hi> the 4. taxed Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> with inſolency for preſuming to take the Crown without his leave. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Ceremonial appointeth that when the Pope rideth abroad the Emperour or chief King that is preſent, or their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors in their abſence ſhould hold his Stirrup, and accordingly ſome Emperors have done it, and have been checked for holding the wrong Stirrup, and if the Pope be diſpoſed to be carried in his Chair, the Emperour, Kings, and their Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors are to put their ſhoulders to it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He exalteth himſelf above all the Miniſtry. <hi>Lanis</hi> the general of the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> maintained in a ſet Lecture at the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> that the ſole power of the Church was committed to <hi>Peter,</hi> and that the other Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their Power from him. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Pope as <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſour hath the ſole power of the univerſal Church, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40317:38"/>all Biſhops, Prieſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> receive their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from him. So that all are but his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, his ſervants, the diſpoſal of all Biſhopricks and benefices (if he pleaſe throughout the world) belongs to him. The power of Excommunication and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, of making and altering all Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal laws and injunctions reſides in him, and to him all appeals muſt be made.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Pope challengeth power over the Devils. They have their book of exorciſmes; the office of exorciſts, their many myſteries, certain prayers, forms of words, Holy water, conſecrated circles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by which they pretend to caſt out, to raiſe, to lay, and bind the Devil as they pleaſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They pretend alſo that the Holy Angels and glorified Saints are at their Command. Pope <hi>Clement</hi> 6. the firſt author of their <hi>Jubilees,</hi> in his Bull, wherein he promiſed great priviledges to all that would come to <hi>Rome,</hi> adds this, <hi>viz.</hi> that if any of theſe holy Pilgrims ſhould chance to die by the way in their journey, he commandeth the holy Angels immediately to tranſport their ſouls to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. The Keys of heaven are one of the Enſigns of the Popes dignity: he can un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaint thoſe that are gone to heaven: he
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40317:39"/>can releaſe out of Purgatory as ſoon, or detain there as long as he pleaſeth. Yea Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the 1. they ſay by his prayers brought the ſoul of <hi>Trajanus</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour out of Hell, 500. Years after he was dead. They interpret the 8. <hi>Pſalm v.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Pope, <hi>viz.</hi> he is that ſon of man that is crowned with glory and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that hath dominion over all the works of God, that hath all things put under his feet, all Sheep and Oxen, <hi>i. e.</hi> all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; all the Beaſts of the field, <hi>i. e.</hi> all the Infidels; the Fowls of heaven, <hi>i e.</hi> the Angels and Saints above; and the fiſh of the Sea, <hi>i. e.</hi> the ſouls in Purgatory.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Pope exalteth himſelf above Chriſt, he challengeth the ſole government of the Church on earth to belong to him, to make and abrogate Laws and to guide it infallibly: ſo that Chriſt now hath nothing to do with the Church militant, he can and daily doth interpret and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with the Laws of Chriſt, and hath authority above his word. When the Pope goes out of Town, the hoſt his breaden God is carried on Horſe-back amongſt his Sumpters and other furnitures a day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand, as one of his utenſils, and in the Church the Pope ſitteth above the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar and above the Hoſt, and giveth it but a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40317:39"/>ſmall nod as he paſſeth by, when the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple give ten times more reverence to him than they do to the Hoſt, even according to their own ceremonies.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He exalteth himſelf above God. He taketh more care to have his own Laws obſerved than Gods commands, and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the violation of them more ſeverely than ſins againſt God. To ſpeak againſt the Pope, the virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or any of their Saints, to work on their Holy-days, to eat fleſh on a faſt-day (eſpecially in <hi>Lent</hi>) are greater offences and harder to be forgiven, than any ſins againſt God. Yea it is the deſign of the Papacy to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt themſelves whatever comes of the honour of God. A man may be of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion or no religion, may live as he pleaſe ſo he own the Popes power and hold the Communion of that Church, and this is all their unity they ſo much brag of. <hi>Papa poteſt omnia quae Deus poteſt,</hi> ſay their Canoniſts, The Pope can do all that God can do; yea and more, as they add, <hi>poteſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere juſtum ex injuſto,</hi> he can make evil good, vice to be vertue, yea every Popiſh Prieſt, they ſay, can make his God and maker out of a piece of bread. A Frier in a Sermon before the Spaniſh Governour at <hi>Milan,</hi> magnifying the Prieſts power
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40317:40"/>ſaid, a Prieſt could do more than God, For God could only make creatures, but every Prieſt could make the infinite God, the maker of all, which God could not do; and yet, ſaith the Authour, this paſſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controul.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle amplifieth this pride in the next words, <hi>he exalteth himſelf ſo as he ſitteth as God in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God, i. e.</hi> he ruleth in the Church of God, and challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth honour from the Church, as if he were God. The Papiſts would hence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that Antichriſt or this man of ſin ſhall be a Leader of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſitting and being worſhipped in their Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to be rebuilt by him; but that Temple ſhall never be rebuilt: when the <hi>Jews</hi> attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted it in <hi>Julians</hi> time, they were hindred by fire breaking out of the earth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending from heaven; and the <hi>Jews</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhall all be converted to Chriſt. The Temple of God here is his Church in which the Man of ſin muſt ſit, who muſt therefore be an apoſtate Chriſtian only, not the <hi>Turk</hi> neither alone, as ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts would have it, nor in conjunction with the Poipe, as ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants think,<note place="margin">Piſcator in Loc.</note> he never was a Chriſtian nor ſitteth in the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40317:40"/>Church, nor endeavoureth to alter or corrupt the worſhip of it, nor aſſumeth divine prerogatives to himſelf, nor was known to the world for many ages after this was written; neither his religion, name, or Nation: whereas this myſtery of iniquity was working in the Apoſtles days; and by him diſcovered and pointed at to the Church. But that the Pope doth ſit in the Church as if he were God, is manifeſt. It is not amiſs to obſerve the word here uſed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he ſitteth in the Temple of God, is the term the Popes uſe. Kings are ſaid to reign, Popes to ſit ſo many years, and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf is <hi>Sedes Apoſtolica,</hi> the Apoſtolical See or Seat.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Pope challengeth an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute univerſal power over the whole world. When <hi>John</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> uſurped the title of univerſal Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the 1. called him the King of pride, the forerunner of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; yet he challenged that title only over the Church; and meant it only of a primacy of order to be the firſt and chief Biſhop: but <hi>Boniface</hi> the 3. ten years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter obtained to be head and univerſal Biſhop, and his ſucceſſours have ever ſince uſed it, exerciſing an abſolute juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both in Civil and Eccleſiaſtical matters.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40317:41"/>The Pope challengeth the diſpoſal of all Kingdoms; if there be any queſtion about ſucceſſion, or any controverſie among Princes, he interpoſeth, and pretendeth to decide all, as having the abſolute power of diſpoſing and ordering all things; and in the Church the ſole authority be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to him of binding and looſing, of appointing Biſhops and Miniſters and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grading them, of conferring all imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, receiving all appeals, not only in reſerved caſes, but in all ordinary caſes when he pleaſes, or the parties pleaſe to remove the caſe to <hi>Rome.</hi> This is a power beyond a mortal man, a charge that no creature can perform, to inſpect and order the affairs of the whole world both of this life and that which is to come.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He challengeth an abſolute power to make laws for the whole Church. Whatſoever he appointeth, though a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Scripture and reaſon, muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted good and be obſerved. He muſt with authority interpret Scriptures, and what he determineth muſt be received as the ſenſe of them. He declareth what is Hereſie and Schiſm, he judgeth all things and perſons, but muſt himſelf be judged of none. Now this is a Divine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40317:41"/>and God's prerogative, that the reaſon and conſciences of men ſhould be ſubject to him. We are to ſubmit our reaſon to God, becauſe he cannot err; and our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to him, becauſe he can command nothing but what is good, yea things are good becauſe he commands them; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Pope in uſurping this power ſits as God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He claims a power to diſpenſe with Gods Laws &amp; to appoint new means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men ſhould come to heaven. He doth frequently diſpenſe with marriages in all the forbidden degrees:<note place="margin">Concil. Trid. Seſ.} 24. <hi>Can.</hi> 3.4.6.</note> and the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> curſeth thoſe that think the Church hath not power to forbid marriage in more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees than the Scripture pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes: or to alter thoſe there ſet down: and to allow marriage in thoſe caſes as it ſhall ſee cauſe. The Scripture ſaith, <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is honourable in all, Heb.</hi> 13.3. but the Pope, ſaith it is not only a diſgrace but a damning ſin for any of the Miniſters of the Goſpel to marry. It is Gods law, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2. to avoid fornication, <hi>every man ſhould have his own Wife and every woman her own Husband:</hi> but the Pope ſaith, it is better for Prieſts to live in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication than to marry; yea and for all
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40317:42"/>perſons 'tis meritorious of heaven to vow not to marry, though they live in all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs: he diſpenſeth with Oaths and vows, and nothing humane or divine is or can he obliging any further than he alloweth it, he being the ſupreme judge, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminer of all things. God alloweth us the uſe of all meats fit for food; but the Pope forbiddeth the uſe of many: yea annexeth merit and the promiſe of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the forbearance of certain meats at certain times, though they gorge and glut themſelves with other ſorts of dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And here let us obſerve that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of an apoſtaſie from the faith that ſhould be in the latter times, <hi>v.</hi> 1. and he giveth this as one character of this apoſtaſie, that theſe apoſtates ſhould forbid marriage, and the uſe of meats in an hypocritical pretence of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs: which doth ſo point out the Papiſts as if they had been named, none but they teaching thoſe doctrines, eſpecially that of forbidding marriage. The Pope maketh it meritorious of pardon, and great immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tys, to wear the habits to certain Monks and Friers, to be buried in a Monks cowle, or in the gown of a Capuchin or Carmelite Frier, but above all to the ſaying of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Ave-maries</hi> or <hi>Pater Noſters</hi> in the 7.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:40317:42"/>chief Churches of <hi>Rome,</hi> which will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſome hundred thouſand years par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He pretends to forgive ſin. The <hi>Jews</hi> could ſay, Who can forgive ſin but God only? and he that tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon him to forgive ſin,<note place="margin">Luke 5.21.</note> maketh himſelf a God. But with the Papiſts, every Prieſt taketh upon him to forgive ſin: yea a man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be forgiven unleſs he be firſt abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Prieſt: much more doth the Pope claim, a power to forgive all ſin, and that not declarative only, to pronounce the promiſes of pardon to the penitent; but authoritative alſo, to give abſolution and heaven to whom he pleaſeth. In his Jubilees he carrieth in his hand a golden hammer to break open Paradiſe for all the Pilgrims that come to <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They do often publiſh and ſell indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences for all manner of ſins: it was one ſpecial thing that ſtirred up the ſpirit of <hi>Luther,</hi> that Frier <hi>Teſelius</hi> came into <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> with indulgencies from <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. publiſhing in all Markets and Fairs that he could grant pardon for all manner of ſins, even though a man had laid with the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary.</hi> The Pope can prevent mens going to Purgatory at all, or ſhorten and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40317:43"/>lengthen their time there as he pleaſeth, though they teach Purgatory to be a place where men muſt ſatisfie for their ſins.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Part.</hi> 3. <hi>tit.</hi> 22. cap. 5.5.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Antoninus</hi> maketh a grave Quere whether the Pope may empty Purgatory and releaſe all the ſouls that be there; and as gravely deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineth, that out of the fulneſs of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er he may without doubt do it, though he thinketh it not expedient he ſhould: and ſo doth the Pope too, for then the private Maſſes and prayers for the dead, (which are a great part of their ſervice, and by which the poor Prieſts get their livelyhood) would ceaſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Pope taketh to himſelf the name and titles of God and Chriſt. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus Deus noſter Papa,</hi> our Lord God the Pope, is the language of their Canon Law. <hi>Paul</hi> the 5. cauſed a triumphal Arch to be ſet up at <hi>Tolentum,</hi> under which he was to enter the City, with this inſcription, <hi>Paulo quinto Vice deo,</hi> to <hi>Paul</hi> the 5. the vice-God. They ſay the Pope is the rock, the foundation of the Church, her head and husband, Lord of Lords and King of Kings <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When ſome among themſelves were offended at theſe blaſphemous titles; Biſhop <hi>Beedle</hi> informs while he was in <hi>Italy</hi> about 70. years ſince, there was a congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40317:43"/>appointed at <hi>Rome</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs theſe abuſes,<note place="margin">Beed. <hi>anſwer to</hi> Wodſw.</note> called <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatio de moderandis titulis;</hi> but before they could do any thing to purpoſe, the Pope forbid them to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, becauſe, he ſaid, there were no titles given him but what, <hi>dignitas &amp; praerogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va Sancti Petri &amp;c.</hi> the dignitys and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives of <hi>Peter</hi> would well enough bear. Thus this Roman State is the Beaſt in whoſe head are the names of Blaſphemy.<note place="margin">Rev. 13.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it appears, though the Pope call himſelf the ſervant of ſervants and the Vicar of Chriſt, yet he doth indeed uſurp the place of Chriſt and the honour and authority of God himſelf; wherefore he is deſervedly accounted the Antichriſt in both ſenſes of the word, <hi>Hoſtis &amp; emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Chriſti,</hi> both the oppoſer of Chriſt and his competitour that contends with him for honour, and uſurps his place and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity. The Apoſtle ſaith, that there were many Antichriſts in the world in his time, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.18. and that the ſpirit of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt was then entered into the world, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.3. and that theſe Antichriſts were apoſtates from the Chriſtian Church. They went out from us, <hi>chap.</hi> 2.19. but yet that there was one ſpecial Antichriſt to come,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:40317:44"/>of which the Church was forewarned, <hi>you have heard that Antichriſt ſhould come, cap.</hi> 2.18. and ſurely there hath never been a more dangerous enemy of Chriſt than this apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate State of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Heathens had but one way of oppoſing Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which tended much to the honour of Chriſt and his grace by the ſufferings of the faithful: but theſe both deſtroy by perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe that are moſt upright, and corrupt and poyſon the reſt by errour, ſuperſtition &amp; Idolatry. The Papiſts plead that Antichriſt ſhall deny both God and Chriſt his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and incarnation, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.22. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.3. But this the Pope doth not: yet the doth it in effect though not in words, when he uſeth and exerciſeth the names, titles, power and office both of the father and the Son, and hath ſet himſelf againſt the pure doctrine, worſhip, and diſcipline of the Goſpel. The Papiſts cannot prove from this or any other place certainly that ſuch an Antichriſt as they deſcribe is to be expected: and we do prove all the properties of Antichriſt to belong to the Pope, even this of denying Chriſt to be come in the fleſh in effect though not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, and yet ſome of them have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Goſpel a fable: and have been profeſſed Atheiſts. If Chriſt rule not his
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40317:44"/>Church, if the Pope be head, with abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute power over it, if Chriſt he daily made of a bit of bread and daily Sacrificed by the Prieſt to make attonement with the Father, as they teach and practiſe, this is in effect to ſay he is not come, nor hath made ſatisfaction to God for the ſins of his people. However we need not contend whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope be: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Antichriſt that what to come, or ſome other Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick may be intended; we are ſure Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt fits the Pope; and we have little more of him than his name, but that he is the man of ſin, the Son of perdition, the author and maintainer of a general apoſtaſie; and that <hi>Rome</hi> is the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> is clear from this place and <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. and this is all the Proteſtants mean by the name of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>V;ſe</hi> From all this we inferr, 1. That pretence of ſome Papiſts that they are of the Church but not of the Court of <hi>Rome, i. e.</hi> for the Romiſh religion, but not for the Popes ſupremacy, is altogether vain. The Pope as Pope claimeth the full pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Chriſt both over the Church and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the world, and if they believe him to be infallible, they muſt believe he hath this power alſo; if he deceiveth them in this, he may deceive them in matters of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40317:45"/>likewiſe. But they that will refuſe the Oaths of Allegiance and ſupremacy, becauſe thoſe deny the Popes juriſdiction over our Kings, and can conſent to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of their perſons and the giving away their Kindoms to ſtrangers, are certainly for the Court as well as for the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Pope is not to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged or reſpected as a temporal Prince. The power he hath is uſurped on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of being head of the Church, which is a power Chriſt never gave, a magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that God never inſtituted; his titles and claims are blaſphemous; he rules as a God not as Gods vicegerent, nor doth he uſe his power for the proper ends of government, to maintain the true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, juſtice, honeſty, or ſobriety among men, and to preſerve the peace of the world, but to ſubvert religion, juſtice, and all morality, and to imbroil all nations for his own intereſt. As a ſociety of <hi>Bandites</hi> or Pirates is no common-wealth, but they are to be reckoned <hi>hoſtis humani generis,</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of mankind; ſo the Pope is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckoned <hi>hoſtis Eccleſia,</hi> the profeſſed irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable enemy of Chriſt: and it is ſome degree of defection to have any commerce with or any reſpect for that Antichriſtian State.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:40317:45"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ver.</hi> 5. The Apoſtle having ſpoke thus much of the man of ſin, calleth the <hi>Theſſ.</hi> to remembrance of what he had ſaid to them about this matter when preſent with them. <hi>Remember ye not that when I was yet with you I told you theſe things? Moſes</hi> forewarned <hi>Iſrael</hi> of a great apoſtaſie, that would be among them; even ſuch as would threaten utter deſtruction, did not God remember his Covenant; and that even then there was ſuch a leaven working a nongſt them. Our Saviour foretold his diſciples that falſe Chriſts and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſhould ariſe, and deceive many; and the Apoſtles in all their Epiſtlesforetell that ſeducers and defections would come in the Church: all which is done to prevent the ſecurity that men are prone to, and that the Godly might both beware of, and be leſs ſtartled at ſuch things when they ſhould ſee them come to paſs.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle adds, <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>and now you know what withholdeth, that he might be revealed in his time.</hi> He had told the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> what would delay the power and revelation of this Man of ſin for a time; that he might not prevail till the appointed time, and then he ſhould diſcover himſelf; for he ſhould not get his power or ſhew his wickedneſs all at once or apparently till ſome letts be remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40317:46"/>out of his way, but ſhould ſecretly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate and grow by degrees till he ſhould come to his full ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Ver. 8. <hi>For the Myſtery of iniquity doth already work: only he who now letteth will lett, untill he be taken out of the way.</hi> Ver. 8. <hi>And then ſhall that wicked be revealed.</hi> The Apoſtle ſaw that there was even in his days ſome beginnings of this Man of ſin, ſome tendency toward the great apoſtaſie; but it was ſecret and a myſtery of iniquity; this is another character of this apoſtaſie, <hi>viz.</hi> that it ſhould be myſterious, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fair pretences. Chriſt and the true doctrine of Salvation are, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the myſtery of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.16.</note> and the apoſtaſie from this faith is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a myſtery of iniquity. The great Whore, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5. had a name written in her <hi>forehead, Myſtery, Babylon the great, the Mother of Harlots, and abominations of the earth.</hi> Though ſhe ſhould be both unclean and wicked her ſelf, and the author of it to all the earth, yet it ſhould be under fair pretences in a myſtery. Some travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers have obſerved amongſt other antiquities at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Du Moul. <hi>Accom. of proph.</hi> Rev. 17.</note> that there are ſhewn ſome ancient Miters of former
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:40317:46"/>Popes, that have the word <hi>Myſterium</hi> in Golden characters upon the front of them; as if ſhe had been ambitious to have the prophecie verified of her ſelf. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle alſo, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. ſaith that the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſie of the latter times ſhould be brought about by men, that talk lies in Hypocriſie, forbidding to marry, and to eat certain meats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This plainly points out the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Heathens, <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> are open and profeſſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of Chriſt, but the Pope is a ſecret and myſtical enemy that betrays Chriſt with a kiſs and under the pretext of friendſhip. Their pretences are ſuch as theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Popes abſolute power is for the honour of Chriſt; that it was fit that he that is Lord of Lords and King of Kings, ſhould have a ſervant or Deputy on earth, who ſhould have Soveraign power over all perſons and cauſes: That his Church ſhould not be ſubject to ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar men and temporal Princes, but to one who is Chriſt's immediate Vicar. They ſay it is not fit the Miniſters of Chriſt ſhould be under the power of men of this world, or that they ſhould judge of Eccleſiaſtical cauſes or diſpoſe of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical imployments, but that all ſhould be managed by a ſpiritual Court and ſpiritual perſon.</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:40317:47"/>
            <p n="2">2. They pretend the benefit of the Church. It is neceſſary, they ſay, that as the Church is one body on earth, though diſperſed in all quarters, ſo it ſhould have one viſible Head, who ſhould be the fountain of Unity, that he ſhould have ſupreme and abſolute power to judge all perſons, and to determine all caſes, to prevent diviſions and to preſerve Unity, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the doctrine and worſhip of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and to prevent or redreſs errors and corruptions; and that things may be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged with ſafety, it is neceſſary this Head ſhould be infallible; who may neither be ſubject to deceive, or be deceived: for what end ſhall there be of Queſtions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies in Religion, or in Civil matters? How ſhall Hereſies, Schiſms, Wars and Seditions be prevented, if there be not a ſupreme infallible head and judge, whoſe authority and deciſion may put an end to all ſtrife and lead into all truth?</p>
            <p n="3">3. They pretend great care of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Salvation. They take away the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from them, for fear they ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane them by uſing them in common diſcourſe; or fall into error and Hereſies by miſtaking the meaning of them; or be puffed up with knowledge, and ſo be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient to their teachers, and run into
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40317:47"/>Sects &amp; diviſions; therefore they give them Images, Crucifixes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which they call Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens books to ſtir up their devotion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger of making them heady or high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded; they allow them little preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and celeberate all the worſhip of God in an unknown tongue, that the people may not grow ſlight and prophane; and that they may ſtill admire what they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, ignorance being the beſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of devotion; and for the greater ſecurity and eaſe they teach them impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citely to believe what the Church believes, and that being infallible they cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve amiſs, eſpecially when they know not in particular what ſhe believeth, nor can call her faith into Queſtion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They pretend great devotion and zeal to Gods worſhip; ſpiritual knowledge, pious affections, ſpiritual worſhip, ſuch as teaching the word, prayer, and uſe of plain Sacraments as Chriſt appointed them, they think are mean things inſtead of theſe they build Temples, adorn Images, adore the bread in the Euchariſt, offer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, Tapers, and many gifts, as more real devotion.<note place="margin">Conc. Trid. Seſ. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent</hi> commands that the Prieſts ſhould carefully teach the people the right uſe of Images, which
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40317:48"/>are to mind them of their Saints, their virtues, and miracles and ſufferings, that they may be ſtirred up thereby to the imitation of them. Their worſhip of the Virgin is devotion to her Son; and their praying to Saints and Angels is honour to God whoſe ſervants they are: and the Pomp and riches of the Pope and his Biſhops is to preſerve the Goſpel in honour, and religion from contempt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They pretend great mortification. They have frequent faſts at leaſt, from fleſh and ſome ſorts of food to curb keep down the fleſh has they pretend. Their voluntary penance, whippings, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages to remote places, confeſſing all their ſins to a Prieſt, and craving his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and all to ſhew their ſorrow for ſin, and to break them off from it more ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than the plain Spiritual means of the word and prayer. It is thought great ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyal to forſake the world, to live in wilderneſſes and Monaſteries, to vow ſingle life, and to refrain thoſe comforts and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments which God hath both allowed and commanded.</p>
            <p n="6">6. They pretend great humility. It is humility in them to be ſubject to their ſuperiours, eſpecially the Pope, againſt their own reaſon and conſcience, and to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:40317:48"/>obey all the commands and ordinances of their Church without preſuming to inquire into the reaſon of them, or to prove them by Scripture. They account it preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to pretend to aſſurance of Salvation, and great humility to live and dye in doubt; but eſpecially that the beſt of them muſt not pretend to go to Heaven but through long ſuffering the pains of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and the help of the prayers of the Church on earth, and of the merits of the Church in Heaven.</p>
            <p n="7">7. They pretend great care to have the Miniſtery pure and induſtrious, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they allow them not to marry, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (ſaid Pope <hi>Ciricius</hi>) they that are in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God: and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing free from the cares of a family, they may wholly attend upon their Miniſtry: and leſt the ſervice of Pariſh Prieſts ſhould not be ſufficient, they have multitudes of Monks and Friars to help them in private, and whoſe prayers and private Maſſes are always going for the benefit of the Church.</p>
            <p>Thus they have plauſible pretences for all their doctrines and practices; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it is a myſtery of iniquity in every particular.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The univerſal power the Pope claimeth is only to ſet up himſelf and his own inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:40317:49"/>therefore he taketh upon him all the ſtate and grandeur of the Roman Emperours, even the proudeſt of them: he gives away Kingdoms when Kings any way diſpleaſe him, though they be very religious towards God; and when he can make any advantage, He ſets Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kings at war with each other, and taketh the unjuſteſt part, ſo it be the ſtrongeſt; yea himſelf raiſeth War and driveth Princes out of their dominions to increaſe the riches of the Church, or to preferr his own Nephews and kindred: This was notorious in <hi>Julius</hi> 2 and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his predeceſſours; he maketh the Emperours ſwear allegiance to him; and the Biſhops at their conſecration uſe to ſwear to maintain <hi>Regalia ſancti Petri,</hi> the royalties of Saint <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The pretence of infallibility is only to gain authority to himſelf, that he may command and do what he pleaſeth in the world it is uſed only to draw people into ſeditions and maſſacres, to patronize any unjuſt actions or claims, when the Pope giveth away the right of a King or other perſon, when he diſſolveth Lawful marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, or giveth diſpenſations to contract unlawful Matrimony (as betwixt Uncle and Niece in <hi>Philip</hi> 2. of <hi>Spain,</hi> or betwixt
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40317:49"/>Brother and brothers Wife as at this day in <hi>Portugal,</hi> the former husband yet living, and the like when he forgives all manner of ſins, when he maketh (as his Canons give him leave) juſt things unjuſt, and ſins to be duties, then he maketh uſe of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended infallibility, and never but it ſuch caſes: for the Popes never do nor never will determine or end any controverſie in religion, for fear of loſing one part of the contenders. There is a great difference among themſelves, betwixt the <hi>Dominicans</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> about the immaculate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the Virgin <hi>Mary; Philip</hi> the 2 and 3. of <hi>Spain</hi> did for many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by their Embaſſadours earneſtly ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licite the Popes to uſe their Infallibility and decide the controverſie, but they could never obtain it. The <hi>Moliniſts</hi> and <hi>Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeniſts</hi> contend as earneſtly about free-will and effectual grace; <hi>Clement</hi> 8. was intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to decide the controverſie; He ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed men to conſider of it, but when they had had fourſcore meetings and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations about it under <hi>Clement</hi> 8. and 1 <hi>Paul</hi> 5. the buſineſs was fairly laid aſide and no determination made. <hi>Innocent</hi> the 10. being deſired to determine the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the five propoſitions, relating to the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40317:50"/>ſame doctrine of the <hi>Janſeniſts,</hi> firſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly told them that he never ſtudied Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in his life, and he was now too old to begin; The <hi>Jeſuites</hi> at laſt having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with him to condemn thoſe propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions without reaſon why, or any expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in what manner, or ſenſe, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned them; he afterwards told the <hi>Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> that defended theſe propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions (as one of themſelves) that he had not condemned the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> which they maintained;<note place="margin">Sanct. amor. Journal.</note> and ſo left the two parties at as great ſtrife as before, what doctrine it was which was condemned and which was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Pope.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They take away the Scriptures from the people meerly to keep them in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that they may guide and govern them the better at their own pleaſure. What if ſome be gluttons and ſurfeit? Muſt therefore all men be deprived of their neceſſary meat and drink? God gave his Law that men might know how to fear and ſerve him; but the Pope pretends they may ſerve God better without knowledge. Why do they not try what effect the reading of the Scriptures will have upon people? Are not their Clergy and Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars as likely to abuſe the Scriptures, to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:40317:50"/>pervert them, to fall into errors and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them by Scripture, as the common people? But they puniſh it with death in the people to have the Bible, or any part of it in their own tongue; and teach that implicite faith is better than explicite, and ignorance than knowledge for the common people, yea they labour to bring the people into an ill opinion and ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the Scriptures; telling them they are obſcure and cannot be underſtood, they have many ſences and like a noſe of wax may be turned many ways, therefore they cannot find the right meaning, yea imperfect and cannot teach them all they are to know and do as neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Beſides the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> authorizeth only the vulgar Latin edition of the Bible for authentick,<note place="margin">Seſ. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> by which all things muſt be tried, though their own men acknowledge that Tranſlation to be moſt corrupt and falſe, and one of them ſaith,<note place="margin">Iſio dorus Clarius.</note> he in his edition had mended eight thouſand faults; ſo that they would allow even their Clergy as little knowledge as they can.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They give the people images, and the Hoſt to worſhip, to take them off from the ſpiritural knowledge and worſhip
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40317:51"/>of Jeſus Chriſt, to make them content without the Bible, to bring them into an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of the Saints, that they only make and canonize, to lead them into all ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition for the gain of the Pope and his Clergy: for what may they not do with the people, when they have perſwaded them to take a bit of bread for their God, to offer their prayers to ſtocks and ſtones inſtead of their maker, or to think that he is pleaſed when they do ſo? When people will take their Mediators, and interceſſors with God, of the Popes appointment, and ſuffer themſelves to be cheated of the knowledge of their Redeemer; when they will content themſelves with offering in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, tapers, Latin prayers and the like, as their ſacrifices to God (which He never commanded and they underſtand not) and be taken off from hearing Gods word, and from praying with underſtanding, when they have brought the people to ſuch a paſs, they may command them what they pleaſe: and this is all they aim at to have them take their religion wholly from the Pope not from the Scriptures, that ſo they may be perfectly ſubject to his will.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Their practices of mortification are only to encreaſe the authority of their Church and Clergy; therefore they muſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:40317:51"/>confeſs to a Prieſt and have his abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that every one may be obliged to have his confeſſour, and hereby the Prieſts both get mony, and alſo know the tempers, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, and ſecrets of all the people; and ſo can teach and uſe them, for their own purpoſes: thoſe that are devout, they lay great penances on them, that by the ſhew of ſtrictneſs and holineſs they may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure the ſimple; if they be vitiouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, they grant them eaſie pardon, and give them great liberty, leſt they ſhould fright them from their communion, and that they may increaſe their hatred againſt the Proteſtants that pretend to more ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The Prieſts from Confeſſions pick all inſtruments for their ſeveral purpoſes, ſome women for <hi>Nuns,</hi> and ſome for Harlots; ſome men for Scholars, ſome for a ſnow of ſtrictneſs, ſome to debauch others, and ſome to murder Princes, and overturn Kingdoms; their penances ſerve only to inſlave men to the Prieſts; their faſts are but mockeries, ſeeing men may eat any thing but fleſh, and that which comes immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately of it, as freely as they will; yet this teaches them obedience to the Church, that they ſhould do as ſhe commands: hence <hi>Bellarmin</hi> makes two ſorts of faſts, <hi>Jejunium virtutis, &amp; Jejunium Eccleſiae,</hi> A Faſt of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:40317:52"/>devotion, and a faſt of the Church, which is obſerved only becauſe ſhe preſcribes it, and ſuch are moſt of theirs. Their pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages bring great gain to thoſe that keep the Shrines they come to viſite; their whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings and auſterities are to cheat their own Conſciences, and other men with a ſhow of mortification, when all the world knows they that make light of fornication, allow ſlews, diſpenſe with vows and marriages at pleaſure, and can forgive any ſins for money, do neither teach nor practiſe real mortification.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Their humble ſubjection to their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours which they call Blind obedience, <hi>Caecam obedientiam,</hi> is a manifeſt trick to bring the people into abſolute ſubjection to their Clergy, and the Clergy to the Pope: up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this pretence the Friars and <hi>Jeſuites</hi> dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſend their Emiſſaries to murder Kings, to divide Nations, to ſpread Hereſies, to take upon them all manner of diſguiſes, to take any Oaths or proteſtations to carry on their deſigns; they teach men to doubt of their Salvation while they live, that they may ſtill depend upon the Prieſt to confeſs and be abſolved, that they may be ſtill under his command and correction, in appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing new ſuperſtitions and penances; and therefore do they teach Purgatory after
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:40317:52"/>their death, that the Pope and his Prieſts may ſtill keep them in their power, and get money for Maſſes, prayers, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonizations.</p>
            <p n="7">7. They forbid their Clergy to marry, not from zeal for holineſs and purity, (ſeeing they allow them fornication) but that having no families to care for, nor any intereſt of their own in the world, the Popes intereſt may become theirs, and their only care may be to advance and ſerve him; that thereby they alſo may be advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and domineer in their places; by this means alſo they are made unnatural, reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and cruel, to proſecute the Popes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, like the Turks <hi>Janizaries,</hi> being kept from thoſe relations which ſweeten mens tempers and excite natural affection; alſo having no wives and children to provide for, they may more deſperately ventuere their lives and their eſtates for the ſervice of their Church.</p>
            <p>Their Friars make a ſhew of great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, renouncing the world, begging alms of the people, going in mean habit, bare-footed ſome of them, yet they get all they can from the people for Maſſes and prayers; their Abbots many are Lords, live ſplendidly, in <hi>England</hi> they had above a third part of the land, and that the beſt,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:40317:53"/>as was made appear to King <hi>Henry</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. but theſe wholly are at the Popes devotion; of theſe he can raiſe Armies, from them he can exact vaſt ſums of money, he can make ſtrong parties in any Nation againſt their Prince, he can turn people which way he pleaſes; In a word; his unmarried Clergy, and Regulars, make him a Monarch, they are his <hi>Populus virorum,</hi> intirely at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, having no poſterity nor perſonal concerns to care for: For if his Clergy had wives and children, they muſt love them, provide for them, diſpoſe of them in marriage, and ſo be neighbourly, oblige the people, pleaſe their Princes and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, contract affinities, and ſo they would be concerned in the ſafety, peace, proſperity of the Nations and places they live in, and would not be at the Popes beck, on at his call upon all occaſions.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee the whole deſign of Popery iſſueth in this; That men ſhould take their religion from the Pope and his Clergy, that ſo they may rule, as ſole Lords, both in ſpirituals and temporals.</p>
            <p>We are next to enquire what it was that letted or hindred Antichriſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing for a time; <hi>He that letteth will lett,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:40317:53"/>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſaith, this myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity was working in his time, therefore it could not be the religion of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> which was not heard of till about the year of our Lord 622. Much leſs Heatheniſm or Judaiſm which were then the eſtabliſht religions of the world; nor yet the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral oppoſition of the body of the wicked againſt the godly; which the Rhemiſts would have underſtood by myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Babylon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rhem. on</hi> Rev. 17.</note> for this is alwaies manifeſt; the ſeed of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent doth always oppoſe the ſeed of the woman: but the Apoſtle ſaw an aſpiring ſpirit in the Biſhops and Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which he knew would in time bring the whole Church under their yoak; this was occaſioned by <hi>Rome</hi>'s being the Metropolis of the world, and the ſeat of the Empire, which as it drew all civil affairs and ſupreme Juriſdiction to that place, ſo did it inſenſibly draw the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, reſpect, and cauſes of all Churches to the guides of that Church, which the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Biſhops challenged as their due, and ſo gave occaſion for the conception of the Man of ſin. <hi>Victor</hi> the 14 Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> about the year 170. excommunicated all the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches for not keeping <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> on the ſame day that he did. Soon after
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:40317:54"/>him <hi>Cornelius</hi> and <hi>Stephen</hi> ſucceſſively took upon them with great pride to determine cauſes belonging to the Churches of <hi>A. frick,</hi> while <hi>Cyprian</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> of which he complains in his Epiſtles to them. Pope <hi>Sylveſter</hi> by his Legats in the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> an. 325. obtained power over all thoſe regions called <hi>Suburbicariae</hi> which were ſubject to the Praefect of <hi>Rome;</hi> and from that time the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> boldly challenged the primacie of all Churches, and drew all cauſes and appeals to themſelves, though not without oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Biſhops in <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time. The Council of <hi>Sardica</hi> having made a Canon that all doctrines ſhould be tried by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> meaning it only for that time when <hi>Rome</hi> was a bulwork a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Arians;</hi> ſeveral Roman Biſhops, <hi>Celeſtine, Boniface</hi> and <hi>Innocent</hi> the firſt thruſt this Canon into the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> and pretended that by authority of that venerable Council, the Tryal of all doctrines and cauſes was given to them; and when the Biſhops of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> challenged a parity with the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe that City was made new <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Seat of the Empire in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> Pope <hi>Leo</hi>'s Legates proteſted againſt it in the Council of <hi>Chalce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Ann.</hi> 450. Thus the ambition of <hi>Rome</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:40317:54"/>diſcovered it ſelf apace, but it could not yet attain its end, becauſe ſomewhat ſtill hindred, and this was the Roman Empire, which divers antient Fathers witneſs to have been the Apoſtles meaning, by <hi>him</hi> that letteth; ſaying that he did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly mention the Empire leſt he ſhould give offence by ſpeaking of the fall of that Empire which they preſumed ſhould laſt for ever, inſomuch that <hi>Roma aeterna</hi> eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Rome</hi> was always written upon the Statue of a woman that repreſented that City, and <hi>Aeternitas Veſtrûm,</hi> your eternity, was a preſumptuous title of ſome of the Emperours; they add that the Primitive Church uſed to pray for the continuance of the Roman Empire, for this reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, that the coming, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions of Antichriſt might thereby he deferred: and <hi>Hierome</hi> who lived to ſee the Empire decay apace, and the City taken by <hi>Alarick</hi> the <hi>Goth,</hi> ſaid thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Qui detinet fit de medio, &amp; non intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Antichriſtum adeſſe?</hi> He that letteth is taken out of the way, and do we not underſtand that Antichriſt muſt be at hand? The <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> would fain avoid this interpretation though they make nonſenſe of the place;<note place="margin">In Locum.</note> but the Papiſts generally acknowledge the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40317:55"/>Empire to be that which letted the diſcovery of Antichriſt; and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would prove that Antichriſt is not yet come, becauſe there is ſtill a Roman Emperour, <hi>viz.</hi> the Emperour of <hi>Germany</hi> who hath the titles of <hi>Roman Caeſar &amp; Auguſtus;</hi> but he hath the empty title only, and is the Popes Vaſſal, receiving his Crown from him, ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fealty to him, and is by him appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Defenſor Eccleſiae,</hi> not to rule the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, but defend the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> That the Empire of <hi>Rome</hi> is here intended is manifeſt by this, becauſe that held the ſupreme dominion, and therefore the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops could not obtain it, till the Empire was aboliſht: the Heathen Emperours op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and deſtroyed the whole Church, and in particular the Biſhops and Church of <hi>Rome</hi> who were neareſt to them, and the Chriſtian Emperours not only kept the civil power in their own hands, but alſo called and preſided in Councils, approved and confirmed the elections of all Biſhops, and thoſe of <hi>Rome</hi> more eſpecially, and removed thoſe Biſhops whom they liked not, at their pleaſure; till this juriſdiction was abrogated, the Pope could not get into his hands the ſupremacie either in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical or civil matters: The event alſo expounds the Text; for by thoſe degrees
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:40317:55"/>the Empire declined, the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> aſcended the throne, as it followeth in the Text, <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>Then ſhall that wicked be revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that wicked or lawleſs perſon; when the reſtraint and laws of the Emperours were taken off, then was the time for the lawleſs perſon to appear, who profeſſeth himſelf ſubject to no law, but above all humane and divine. The remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the imperial ſeat from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Byzan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium</hi> by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great gave the firſt advantage to the aſpiring minds of thoſe Biſhops, for then the eyes of all were up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them inſtead of the Emperours, then they diſdained to come to Councils, and ſet Ambaſſadours in their names, two or three at a time in Princely manner, then they cried up the dignity and primacy of <hi>Peter,</hi> and of the Apoſtolick See, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated themſelves into the affairs of all Churches; again when <hi>Rome</hi> was ſackt by the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> and the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours power decayed in <hi>Italy,</hi> the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> aſſumed more authority to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and were ready to comply with bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians and invaders againſt their natural and Chriſtian Prince to increaſe their own power. When <hi>Odoacer</hi> had taken <hi>Rome</hi> and made himſelf King of <hi>Italy,</hi> Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi> joyned with him, called a Council of ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:40317:56"/>Biſhops at <hi>Rome,</hi> and preſided in it in the preſence of the uſurper, <hi>Ann.</hi> 570. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this when the Imperial race was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extinguiſht in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> by the impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tyrant <hi>Phocas, Boniface</hi> 3. readily joyns with him, writes flattering letters to him, and obtained of him the long deſired title of univerſal Biſhop, <hi>Ann.</hi> 606. And now the Emperours are beholding to the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> to hold their dominion in <hi>Italy;</hi> yet this was a Clog to them that their election muſt be approved by the Emperours; when therefore they had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with <hi>Conſtantine</hi> 4. to releaſe them of this obligation, and to grant, that whom the Senate and people of <hi>Rome</hi> choſe, he ſhould be received as Pope without asking the Emperours conſent, then they had perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhaken off the yoak; and the following Popes, <hi>Gregory</hi> the 2. and 3. excommunicated 2. Emperours, <hi>Philippicus</hi> and <hi>Leo,</hi> for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Image worſhip, abſolved their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from their Oath of allegiance, and raiſing war againſt them, finally drove them out of <hi>Italy</hi> about the year 750. Yet the <hi>Lombards</hi> troubled the Pope, till he called in <hi>Pipin</hi> who ſubdued them, and his Son <hi>Charles</hi> the great, who put an end to their Kingdom. And now the Pope was Lord of <hi>Italy,</hi> and giveth <hi>Charles</hi> the tile of Roman
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:40317:56"/>Emperour, and after about 6 generations he tranferred it to the <hi>Germans.</hi> And now the Pope had a new and his laſt difficulty; theſe <hi>German</hi> Emperours challenged the confirmation of the Popes election and the inveſting of all Biſhops within their dominons, but the Pope was grown ſo ſtrong, that by plain force and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all wars he at laſt compelled the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours to renounce all power over the Popes, and <hi>Italy</hi> it ſelf, to reſign the inveſtiture of all Biſhopricks to the Pope, yea to have his own election confirmed by the Pope, and to hold his Crown as his gift, which was principally managed though not finiſhed by <hi>Hilderbrand,</hi> Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> 7. about the year 1077. And now the man of ſin was revealed indeed and come to maturity, and from his time divers learned men of every nation declared and proved the Pope to be Antichriſt, and ever ſince the Pope hath filled all the <hi>Weſt</hi> with wars, Maſſacres and the private murders of his inquiſition, to uphold the power he had ſo honeſtly gotten: he hath alſo made attempts upon the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches, and he gained ſome power over them while the <hi>Latines</hi> reigned in <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> but that fell with them, and the <hi>Eaſt</hi> hath been oppreſſed by the <hi>Turk</hi> as the <hi>Weſt</hi> by the Pope, though not altogether in ſo
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:40317:57"/>terrible a manner; for he for money grants the Chriſtians their Churches and exerciſe of their religion, but the Pope will ſuffer none to live that will not ſubmit to him.</p>
            <p>It may juſtly be a wonder how it was poſſible the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> many of them mean and inferiour men, and many moſt flagitious, could poſſibly attain ſo great power and dignity,</p>
            <p>It was a myſtery, ſaith the Apoſtle, and it was done inſenſibly. At firſt the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> were eminent for parts, piety, and ſufferings, as uſually ſuch men are preferred and imployed in great, eſpecially Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical Cities; this gained them great credit with all Churches, and both Miniſters and people had them in great veneration, and deſired their judgement and counſel in weighty caſes; then the Emperours, new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly become Chriſtian, thought they could not beſtow honour and power enough up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church, eſpecially on the Imperial ſeat; they granted them their Courts, their Apparitors, and attendance, with leave to all Chriſtians to bring their cauſes to their Courts; this made them Pettie-Princes; then they challenged the right of appeals from all Churches, though op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and ſhamefully foiled by the Churches of <hi>Africk;</hi> they would receive
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:40317:57"/>any perſons and cauſes into their patronage, the more unjuſt, the better for them; for the criminal perſons having no hope of redreſs in their own Churches, wholly relied upon the Popes authority, and he to increaſe his authority would do his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt for them; and this was the reaſon why the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> who long main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the true doctrinal worſhip, at length ſet up image worſhip, Tranſubſtantiation, and all the reſt of their ſuperſtitions, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe the promoters and defenders of theſe corruptions fled to the Popes autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to ſhelter themſelves from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and cenſure of the ſounder part of the Church, and the Pope ſtill ſided with the worſt that thereby he might oppreſs thoſe who would not acknowledge his univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and ſupremacy; at laſt the Pope hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by theſe means inſinuated into the minds and affections of the worſt, but greater part, he did by force eſtabliſh his throne above all, and by force he hath kept it: moreover the ſloth and ignorance of may in the miniſtry, and the pride of others, who ſought to advance themſelves, by advancing the Pope, did not a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to his power; alſo the confuſions of the Empire by the invaſions of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians much helpt it forwards, for they
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:40317:58"/>overturned the government, deſtroyed the more knowing people, in themſelves being both <hi>Pagans</hi> and void of all learning, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Religion from the Pope and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition together, and ſuffered themſelves to be inſlaved by him, under the pretence of obedience to Chriſt and is chief Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and his ſucceſſours, and their poor Princes ſuffered their people to be deceived, and were deceived themſelves by theſe plauſible arts; inſomuch that they gave up their power to that Roman beaſt, and thought it good ſervice to Chriſt, when they could ſerve his pretended Vicar; 'tis reported that 30 Kings and Queens of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have left their Kingdoms and gone to <hi>Rome</hi> to ſee St <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor and to die there. A fair warning to Princes and magiſtrates to maintain their own power, and the dignity of their places; and to all Miniſters to look to their own charge; and to the people to be ſubject to their own paſtours, and to take heed of admiring and hearkning after others; if this had been done, the Pope had never got the Chair.</p>
            <p>Hitherto the Apoſtle hath given the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Antichriſt, and ſoretold his inſolency, and Tyranny over the Church, to teach Chriſtians what to expect, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:40317:58"/>to arm themſelves with patience and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarge. Now to prevent deſponding he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels his deſtruction, <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>Whom the Lord ſhall comſume with the ſpirit of his month, and ſhall deſtroy with the brightneſs of his coming.</hi> The deſtruction of this man of ſin is as certain to be in due time, as his coming was: the Lord ſhall conſume him <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; as this wicked one is in ſpecial manner an enemy to Chriſt, ſo Chriſt will ſet himſelf to deſtroy him, will conſume, utterly deſtroy, as Armies lay waſt a Country that they invade; the means by which he will do it, is by the ſpirit of his month, <hi>i. e.</hi> his word, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied by his ſpirit; and we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that no other means have been very ſucceſsful, either to hinder the growth, or to haſten the ruine of the man of ſin: the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Emperours with all their power oppoſed the <hi>Gregories,</hi> and in the <hi>Weſt</hi> the <hi>Othos, Fredericks</hi> and <hi>Henries</hi> oppoſed the Popes in their time, but all to their own deſtruction; the people being bewitcht, and Princes too, by the inchantments of the Great Whore; but when the appointed time was come, a few inconſiderable men, <hi>Luther</hi> and his fellows, only by preaching the word, in the ſpace of about 40. years rent from the Pope half his Empire, and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:40317:59"/>weakned him in all the remaining parts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; many in all Countries, receiving the knowledge of the truth, and both Princes and people that ſtill adhere to him ſtanding in much leſs fear of him, and paying him much leſs homage and ſubjection than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: Again ſince the firſt reformation, though powerful Princes and many Nations have imbraced the Goſpel, and have made ſome attempts by power and arms to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote it, and have had ſome very fair oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities (as when <hi>Hen.</hi> the 4.a Proteſtant was made King of <hi>France,</hi> and conquered all his oppoſers; and in the late <hi>German</hi> wars) yet nothing conſiderable hath been done, but as to particular perſons there hath rather been a loſs in this laſt age, and a great indifferency hath grown upon the Proteſtant Churches. The time when this ruine ſhall be conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted is here expreſt, by the brightneſs of his coming, {fo}, by the appearance of his preſence; as the man of ſin was conceived, born and grew up by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, ſo he hath been, and gradually ſhall be deſtroyed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt by his word and ſpirit preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a ſelect number in all times that oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, and bore Teſtimony againſt him both by word and ſufferings; ſome Princes, ſome learned, many both of the Clergy
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:40317:59"/>and people proteſted againſt the encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and impoſitions of the Popes, whilſt they were contending for the univerſal Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of the Church; and when they had gained it and thought all ſure, about <hi>Ann.</hi> 1160. God raiſed the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> and <hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſes</hi> to bear witneſs againſt them, who ſpread themſelves into <hi>France, Italy, Bohemia, Auſtria, England,</hi> and could never be extinguiſht, till their doctrine ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up a great part of Popery, as <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Rod did thoſe of the Magicians. Thus it was propheſied, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1-6. <hi>v.</hi> that there ſhould be one hundred forty four thouſand under the Tyranny of the beaſt who kept themſelves undefiled, Virgins, who followed the Lamb whitherſoever he went, and kept his Fathers name in their fore head, not ſubmitting to the mark of the beaſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2.A As the fall of this man of ſin draws nearer, ſo the word hath greater ſucceſs, and turneth Nations and rulers to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of it. God diſpenſeth his grace gradually according to the times he hath appointed: from the flood, for above one thouſand years it was reſtrained moſtly to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation, then our Lord ſent his Apoſtles to teach all Nations, but it was ſeveral hundred years before the Nations became Chriſtian, though there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:40317:60"/>Chriſtians in them, and no ſooner had they received the Goſpel but it began to be darkned by the invaſion of <hi>Pagans, Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> by the fraud and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of <hi>Mahomet</hi> and his followers, and moſtly by errors and ſuperſtitions in the Church it ſelf, which bred and brought forth the Pope, and he at laſt ſcaled up the Bible, and quite changed Chriſtian religion into a new ſort of <hi>Paganiſm;</hi> then for about 350. years the truth was forced into corners, but few received and owned it, in compariſon of the world that wondred after the beaſt; ſince that time whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have been enlightened.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt will yet more enlighten by the preaching of his word, till all Nations ſhall ſee the frauds and corruptions of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and abhor them: there will come a time when the Kingdoms of this world ſhall be the Kingdoms of our Lord and his Chriſt, and he ſhall reign for ever and ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. Not only the godly, but the generality of men alſo ſhall believe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the cheats of the Pope, the falſe doctrines and deluſions of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and ſhall no more be enticed by them, and they ſhall love the godly, and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubmit to the pure doctrine, worſhip and diſcipline of the Goſpel, though they have been ſo unwilling to receive it hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:40317:60"/>
            <p n="4">4. Chriſt will ſtir up the ſpirit of Princes to deſtroy <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf and that wicked Polity, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.16. <hi>The Kings of the earth ſhall hate the whore and burn her fleſh with fire:</hi> As the Kings for their own intereſt and private deſigns chieſly, though under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of devotion, advanced the Pope, till he was able to tread upon all their necks; ſo ſome for their own intereſt, and by reaſon of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations from <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhall in due time be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed againſt her and utterly deſtroy her.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And by this means the Tyranny, inſinuations, and intereſts of the Pope and the Princes that joyned with him, being removed and diſſolved, the Goſpel ſhall have its free paſſage, and the Church its full liberty. Many learned men have inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted this place of Chriſts deſtroying the man of ſin by the brightneſs of his coming, of Chriſts coming to the laſt judgement, as if the Pope &amp; his Tyranny ſhould continue at leaſt in part till then, and be utterly aboliſht on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Chriſts perſonal coming to judgement: but it is uſual in ſcripture to expreſs great changes in Church or State by the coming and appearance of the Lord; particularly the deſtruction of the <hi>Jews</hi> for rejecting Chriſt, is expreſt by the Prophets <hi>Joel</hi> and <hi>Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie</hi> in ſuch phraſes that have occaſioned ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to interpret them of the laſt judgement;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:40317:61"/>our Saviour alſo, <hi>Math.</hi> 24, 25. <hi>ch.</hi> expreſſeth his judging of that Nation in like phraſes, and calls it his coming, and commands his ſervants to watch and prepare for it; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. the ſubduing of the heathen world to Chriſt by the Emperours recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Goſpel, and eſtabliſhing it for the publick religion, is ſet out as if it were to be the end of the world, and ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation to ſeiſe upon men as if the end of all things were come upon them. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures foretel in many words and with many circumſtances the fall of <hi>Myſtical Babylon,</hi> which is <hi>Rome,</hi> and moſtly in the ſame words that foretold the ruin of old <hi>Babylon,</hi> as is plain by comparing the 51. <hi>ch.</hi> of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> with the 18. <hi>chap.</hi> or <hi>Rev.</hi> and this is ſpoken both to deter men from complying with <hi>Rome,</hi> and encourage the godly to patience in their ſufferings under her Tyranny; but all this is needleſs in a great meaſure if no more were intended than to tell the world that <hi>Rome</hi> and her power ſhould be deſtroyed when the whole world ſhould end; moreover it is propheſied, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.16. that <hi>the ten Kings that gave their power to the beaſt,</hi> i.e. ſome of them, <hi>ſhall take the Whore, eat her fleſh and burn her with fire:</hi> chap. 18.2. An Angel again foretells that <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould be caſt down with violence <hi>as a great mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:40317:61"/>into the Sea,</hi> and never riſe again, which were no wonder if this were not to be till the end of the world. It is alſo ſaid <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3. as it was of old <hi>Babylon,</hi> that all unclean and hateful birds ſhould lodge in the ruines of <hi>Rome: v.</hi> 4, 5. Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands his people to come out of her that they may not partake of her plagues: <hi>v.</hi> 6. they are commanded to be the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of Gods wrath upon her, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward her double for all that ſhe hath done to them: <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9. ſome of the Kings that ſtill adhered to her with others of all ſorts are deſcribed to make great lamentation o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her, <hi>when they behold the ſmoak of her burning;</hi> and <hi>chap.</hi> 19. is a triumphant Song of the Church for Chriſts victory over <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> and their deliverance from her: theſe things are certain, and ſhow that the Church ſhall be delivered both from the ſeducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and perſecution of the Pope, ſome time before the end of the world; and it is very probable that the thouſand years peace of the Church foretold <hi>chap.</hi> 20. is to ſucceed the fall of <hi>Rome:</hi> all other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures about it are already confuted by the event; and that it cannot be meant of heaven is evident from this, that <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> are to make inſurrection againſt the Church a little before the thouſand
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:40317:62"/>years expireth, and the general judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is deſcribed to follow ſoon after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. This ſhould keep men from embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and perſuade them to forſake the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh religion: It is as all other carnal things be, a periſhing Religion; that Church Chriſt hath promiſed to deſtroy, and that with a deſolation proportionable to all the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence and pomp ſhe hath enjoyed, with an overthrow that ſhall make a change as if the world were ending.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let the godly ſtrengthen their pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in bearing all her violence and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions; there is an appointed end, <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall as certainly fall, and her power and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy be broken, as old <hi>Babylon</hi> was ruin'd, which was once the terror of the world, and had held the Empire near fourteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, longer than <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall; the blood and ſufferings of the Saints ſhall be revenged upon <hi>Rome</hi> abundantly, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.7, 8. and they ſhall have abundant joy in her deſtruction and their own deliverance, even ſuch as <hi>Iſrael</hi> had when they were eſcaped out of <hi>Egypt</hi> thorow the Red Sea, and ſaw all their enemies dead on the ſhore, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The godly both miniſters and people ſhould be encouraged to oppoſe and ſtrive againſt Popery to the utmoſt; their labour
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:40317:62"/>ſhall not be in vain: Chriſt will conſume the man of ſin by his word in their mouths, and in time engage the Princes that now favour her to deſtroy her; the preaching and writing of godly miniſters, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours and ſufferings of godly people are ſo many Teſtimonies againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> and do weaken her intereſt, and ſhall in time be all revived and prevail for her ruin, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all her arts and force and cruelties to preſerve her ſelf, of which we have a pledge, in that by theſe means ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Kingdoms and Nations have already for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken her.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Though there be no power and ſtrength to defend the Church and the truth, though few ſhould be valiant for it, fear not, the word and ſpirit of Chriſt will turn about the hearts of Princes and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to hate the Whore in due time: the work is Chriſts own, he hath undertaken it and who can reſiſt his ſpirit, when he will turn the hearts of men? It ſeemeth that <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall have great probability of prevailing over the Church of Chriſt, and great confidence of her own proſperity im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before her fall, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.7, 8. <hi>She ſaith in her heart, I ſit as Queen, and am no Widow, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall her plagues come in one day, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:40317:63"/>even as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did moſt diſtreſs <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and was moſt confident of ſucceſs the night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his ruin; this very confidence of <hi>Rome</hi> and her laſt rage againſt the Church will engage God to its defence, and provoke the world to her deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Ver. 9. <hi>Even him whoſe coming is after the working of Satan, with all power, and ſigns and lying wonders: v.</hi> 10. <hi>And with all deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are deſcribed the arts and methods by which the man of ſin ſhould attain his greatneſs and deceive the world, partly that we may be the more aware of him, and partly to ſet out the power of Chriſt, and the efficacy of his word, by whom he ſhall be deſtroyed, notwithſtanding all his arts and policies to preſerve himſelf: his coming ſaith the Text, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> his appearing, and attaining ſupremacy in the Church is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to the effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al working of the Devil; the Devil ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhewed ſo much art and contrivance in the erecting of any power, or State, as in that of the Popedom; for beſides force the uſual methods whereby the four for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer great Monarchies were raiſed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, which alſo the Pope made uſe of, here are other peculiar methods ſuited to the nature of a religious Monarchy,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:40317:63"/>or Tyranny under pretence of religion; theſe are, all power, ſigns and lying won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; which are various expreſſions of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles and miraculous operations to gain credit to their Doctrine and pretences, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, with all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous deceits and cheats; as <hi>Moſes</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and confirmed his law and inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions by miracles and wonders, and Chriſt with his Apoſtles confirmed the Goſpel with ſigns and wonders and divers miracles and gifts of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.4. ſo Antichriſt endeavored to prove his power, errors and ſuperſtitions by miracles, ſigns, and wonders; ſo the words here uſed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifie; but the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is great betwixt them; the miracles of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles, were real, weighty and uſeful things, frequent and innumerable, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to all the world, expoſed to the Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and examination of all, and ſuch as carried an undeniable evidence, and divine impreſs with them; but theſe of Antichriſt are lying wonders, ungodly cheats, many of them ridiculous trifles, of no uſe, unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming the finger of God, that are done in a corner, and will bear no Tryal of judicious men, but are fitted only to deceive the ignorant multitude; it is not to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:40317:64"/>that Papiſts could ever work any real ſign or miracle to confirm their falſehoods, for that were to make God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (who alone is the author of true mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles) to bear Teſtimony to a lye, and alſo to invalidate the Teſtimony of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, when they are wrought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the truth, ſeeing they may be wrought alſo to prove a lye. A falſe prophet may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed give a ſign, foretell ſome future event by art, and God may ſuffer that ſign to come to paſs, to prove his people whether they will ſtick to his word, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. but he will never interpoſe his immediate power to work a miracle to confirm falſe doctrine, which were to ſet his own ſeal to that which is contrary to his own word; the miracles and ſigns therefore that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts pretend to, ſome of them are the meer works of nature, only ſtrange to the common people, ſome are works of art, Phyſick, Mathematicks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſome are meer tricks of Legerdemain, and ſome are more lies, without either foundation in the things, or colour of truth, many of them alſo are wrought by Magick and aſſiſtance of the Devil, as when they cauſe doleful cries and howlings in the night, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions of perſons deceaſed, to make the ſimple believe that the ſouls in Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:40317:64"/>come forth to beg prayers and Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which practice was very frequent in <hi>Luthers</hi> time: The pretence of ſigns and miracles is peculiar to the Papiſts; the <hi>Turks,</hi> to whom they would turn this prophecie, profeſs them not, but impoſe and propagate their Religion by force; Chriſtians that own the Scriptures for the perfect rule of faith and manners, need them not, the matter of thoſe Scriptures having been abundantly confirmed long ſince by unqueſtionable miracles and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine atteſtations; but the Papiſts who add unwritten, uncertain traditions, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Popes and Councils to the rule, have need to confirm them by ſigns and miracles, if they could; and upon the pretence of theſe all their chief doctrines are built, as,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Tranſubſtantiation and adoration of the Hoſt; for this they pretend ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that the Hoſt hath been ſeen to bleed, ſometimes that the hand of a child hath been ſeen in it; that <hi>Wittikin</hi> the <hi>Saxon</hi> King in <hi>England</hi> ſeeing Chriſtians receive the Sacrament in a certain Church, went out and reported, that he ſaw the Chriſtians each one put a little ſmiling boy into their mouths; ſome affirmed that they have ſeen a youth in a glorious ſhape ſitting upon the Altar at or before the time of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:40317:65"/>celebration; and they commonly tell us of Cows, Horſes, Bees, yea and the Aſs of a <hi>Jew</hi> or a Heretick, adoring the Hoſt, and the bees building a wax chappel o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it when it was caſually loſt in the field.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The worſhip of Saints; when the invocation of Saints was oppoſed in its beginning, and Pope <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Council at <hi>Rome</hi> to conſider on it, <hi>Ann.</hi> 1012. <hi>Edwin</hi> a Monk of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> made Oath before the Council that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> appeared to him in a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in great glory; commanding him to go to <hi>Rome</hi> and tell the Pope that it was the command of God that they ſhould worſhip her, pray to her, and erect Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Images in honour of her; upon this acknowledgement the Council eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht the firſt decree for the invocation of her and other Saints: They write whole Legends of Saints, their apparitions, revelations, miracles, and theſe they give to the people to read inſtead of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; they alſo read the acts and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wonders of their Saints, upon their feſtival days in their Churches, always concluding their fabulous narrations with ſuch words: Let us then learn to admire ſuch a Saint, let us pray to ſuch a Saint,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:40317:65"/>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Saint <hi>Francis</hi> and his-Friars, they ſay, have raiſed above a thouſand men from the dead; their Saints heal all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of diſeaſes, caſt out Devils, can bring fire from heaven, as they report, and theſe are the proofs of Divine worſhip due to them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their worſhip of Images, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of Saints; to this purpoſe they pretend that ſome Images do ſpeak, though it is the Devil or the Prieſt that ſpeaks through them; ſome Images nod their head; ſome hold up their hand, as if they did bleſs the people that pray to them; Mr. <hi>Downame</hi> ſaith he ſaw an Image of St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> at <hi>Cheſter,</hi> who would lift up his hand, as if he bleſt his petitioners, which was done by a ſtring put through the arm, by which the Prieſt draw'd it up. Some Images have bled, they ſay, when they have been abuſed; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes have been cured and all manner of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles done, while men have been praying before Images.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Purgatory and prayers for the dead: The only proof of this is the apparition of perſons deceaſed, that complain of their torments and beg Maſſes and prayers of their ſurviving friends; to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they make great uſe of the Vulcans <hi>i. e.</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:40317:66"/>burning Mountains in <hi>Italy, Sicily,</hi> and the Iſles of the <hi>Aeolides,</hi> where are heard frequent noiſes of divers kinds, which they tell the people are the gates of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, and the noiſes the cries of the tormented there. They report of one <hi>Birſtan</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> that as he was walking according to his cuſtome in the Church-yard at midnight, earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly praying for the ſouls in Purgatory, when he came to thoſe words <hi>requieſcant in pace,</hi> let them reſt in peace, he ſuddenly heard the voices of an innumerable company, ſmall and great, in the graves ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Their religious orders: St. <hi>Benedict,</hi> St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> St. <hi>Francis,</hi> the founders of ſo many Orders of Friars, and <hi>Ignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Loyola,</hi> the Father of the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> all obtained both the honour of Saints, and of Founders of religious Orders by many pretended viſions, revelations and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; and the opinion of miracles done by Friars, Monks and Nuns, in every generation, is that which keeps up their authority with the people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> This ſhould warn men to cleave cloſe to Scripture; Revelations and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles are the engines of deceit, but writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten truths are manifeſt and expoſed to the conſideration and Tryal of all; and have
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:40317:66"/>been already confirmed by the Prophets, our Saviour and his Apoſties, by very many and unqueſtionable ſigns and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; f men will not be content with this, which God hath ſo abundantly teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to be his mind and will, it is juſt with him to ſuffer them to be deluded; if there be now any miracles, revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or extraordinary impreſſions of the holy ſpirit, they are of private concern, for direction or encouragement in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular caſes, but they are not intended to confirm any doctrine or part of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; ſigns and Tongues, and ſo other miracles are for them that believe not, who have not received the Goſpel, but not to them that believe (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.21, 22.) who have already been convinced of the truth and fulneſs of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to which God expects they ſhould yield their full aſſent and obedience.</p>
            <p>Ver. 10, 11, 12. <hi>In them that periſh; becauſe they received not the love of the truth, that they might be ſaved: and for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſion, that they ſhould believe a lie: that they all might be damned who believed not the truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words we have the ſubject of Antichriſts deluſions, thoſe on whom his
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:40317:67"/>ſigns and lying wonders ſhould have effect, <hi>viz.</hi> they that periſh; though many of the godly may have been entangled by Popiſh ſuperſtitions, yet none receive them throughly, or give up themſelves to them, but thoſe that are to periſh. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.11. They that dwell on the earth wondred after the beaſt, even they whoſe names were not written in the book of life. We have alſo here the reaſon why God ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſo many to be delivered to their own deſtruction, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe they receive not the love of the truth that they might be ſaved; and this is further amplified <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and for this cauſe, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe they love not the truth, God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, deluſions that ſhall be effectual to make them believe a lie, who believed not the truth, <hi>i. e.</hi> obeyed not the truth, <hi>but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, that ſo they might be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gods judgements are ſuitable to mens ſins; thoſe that love not the truth, he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth to loſe the truth, and they that are willing to receive falſe doctrines, and falſe worſhip, that they may more quietly practiſe unrighteouſneſs, God ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth them to have temptations to it, and to be prevailed with by thoſe temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations;
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:40317:67"/>and this is the caſe of the Papal world, becauſe men delight not in the true knowledge of God, to fear him, and be thankful, therefore he gave them up to worſhip Images, and to ſerve the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures more than the Creator; as he dealt with the Heathens before them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21.25. Men lov'd not the knowledge of Chriſt, valued not his love and death, but loved to boaſt of their own wills, abilities and performances, therefore God ſuffered them to loſe the ſound doctrine of juſtification, faith an aſſurance, and to make men and Angels their Mediators, and to truſt in the merits of their own works and ſufferings; men had no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in holineſs, but in unrighteouſneſs and licentiouſneſs, therefore God ſuffered them to be deprived of the Scriptures the mean and rule of holineſs, and to ſpend their days either in will worſhip, ſuperſtition, and voluntary ſeverities, bodily exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, which profits not, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. or elſe in all filthineſs and profaneneſs, and yet to delude themſelves with the vain hopes of pardons, indulgencies, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, penances, and venial ſins. Moreover becauſe men delighted not in ſpiritual things and heavenly mindedneſs, they were deprived of the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:40317:68"/>of heaven, and the comfortable hopes of Salvation, to be taught to live in endleſs doubts and fears that can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſatisfied, and to count it a favour to go to Purgatory at laſt, there to ſuffer ſome thouſands of years the torments of hell, and to believe that their deliverance from thence depends upon the will of Popes and Prieſts, and is to be bought with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Men were weary of the ſpiritual wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, Faith and love, prayer and thankſ giving, hearing the word and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Sacraments with a ſerious heart and deſire to profit by them, therefore they are given up to be content to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of Gods word, and to hear little but the lying miracles of feigned Saints and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Traditions, and commandments of men, alſo to have their prayers and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in a language they do not underſtand, and to fool themſelves with a belief that the <hi>Opus operatuns,</hi> their bare preſence at them and performance of the outward work, is ſufficient to ſave them: Laſtly becauſe men were weary of a pious, profitable and learned miniſtry, therefore they are delivered to be enſlaved by a generation of men, for the moſt part, abominably wicked, ignorant, and ſuperſtitious, who deceive the people and are themſelves
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:40317:68"/>deceived: briefly, natural conſcience will not ſuffer men to be content without ſome religion, and ſome hope of a better life, and ſome perſons to inſtruct them in it; but their unruly luſts and affections make them love and chuſe a religion that they may play and trifle with, and ſuch is Popery, where men may ſeem very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout and zealous in external worſhip, and for the Traditions of their fathers, and yet live in all wickedneſs, and notwithſtanding hope to go to heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. This may leſſen our wonder that Popery ſhould ſo much prevail upon the world, and that men ſhould be ſo ready to return to it after they have received the knowledge of the truth, and Popery been diſcovered to be falſe and ridiculous to common reaſon: it is the righteous judgement of God to ſuffer them to be deceived who would be deceived, and to ſuffer them to take up a falſe and abſurd religion, who are weary of the true, though moſt excellent and moſt rational: for this reaſon no means can withdraw men from their ſuperſtitious and Idolatrous practices, and from their brutiſh obedience to the Pope and their Prieſts, becauſe God hath given them eyes that cannot ſee, and ears
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:40317:69"/>that cannot hear, and hearts that cannot perceive and underſtand, till he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted all his wrath upon them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The beſt means to be preſerved from Popery is to maintain in our ſelves love to the truth. It was want of this that provoked God to give up the world to deluſions, and ſtill to continue it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of them in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. <hi>He that will do the will of him that ſent me, he ſhall know of the doctrine whether it be of God,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 7.17. Scripture and reaſon will not ſuffer us to receive Popery as a truth, or as any religion; but as a meer humane device to keep up the power of the Pope and his adherents, and ſenſe also will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute ſome of their errors, as Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation and many of their miracles; but if we love not the truth, intereſt or fear may make us willing to believe a lye and ſubmit to it: unfeigned love of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and a lively ſenſe of ſpiritual things will prevent this, that we ſhall not be willing to let go the truth, and then God will not ſuffer us to be led into errors. If we delight in the knowledge of God, he will never ſuffer us to be bewitcht with Idols, that can neither ſee, nor hear, nor help.</p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:40317:69"/>
            <p>If Chriſt be precious to us, the chiefeſt of ten thouſands and altogether lovely, God will never ſuffer us to put our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in Creatures, as our Mediators, or in our own works, which would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us.</p>
            <p>If we have pleaſure in drawing night to God; if his word and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be more to us, than our appointed food, our Heavenly Father will not inſtead of it, give us a ſtone of Popiſh auſterities and bodily ſervice, and unintelligible or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, much leſs will he give us the Scorpions of their idolatrous worſhip.</p>
            <p>If we earneſtly purſue the lively hope of heaven and aſſurance of Gods favour, we ſhall never receive the tormenting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion of Purgatory.</p>
            <p>And if they that bring the glad tidings of the Goſpel are moſt welcome to us, God will never ſuffer us to be deluded into a ſlaviſh ſubjection to and fears of the Popes Bulls, and an idolatrous Maſs-Prieſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Apoſtle concludes this diſcourſe, <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>Therefore brethren ſtand faſt, and hold the Traditions which ye have been taught, whether by word, or our Epiſtle:</hi> And this would be a ground to expect what he prays for in their behalf, <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17. <hi>Now our Lord
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:40317:70"/>Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, and God even our Father, which hath loved us, and hath given us everlaſting conſolation, and good hope through grace, Comfort your hearts and ſtabliſh you in every good word and work.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:40317:70"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached <hi>November</hi> 5. 1678.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rev. 18.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And I heard another voice from heaven, ſaying Come out of her my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the former Chapter we have a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> and a prediction of her ruin, in this Chapter; her fall is more at large declared, 1. from the certainty of it, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2, 3. a mighty Angel proclaiming that <hi>Babylon</hi> is fallen, is fallen, as if it were done already, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeconding him with the Type of a Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:40317:71"/>thrown into the Sea, to ſhew that <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould never riſe more, <hi>v.</hi> 21, 22, 23. 2. From the reaſon of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe both <hi>the Kings of the Earth had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted fornication with her and where delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by her, v.</hi> 4. Thirdly, from a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to Gods people to forſake her, <hi>leſt they ſhould be conſumed with her,</hi> v. 4, 5. Fourthly, From a command to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutioners of Gods vengeance to be very ſevere in it, <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7, 8. Fifthly, from a deſcription of the Lamentation of her friends for her fall, <hi>v.</hi> 9,—19. Sixthly, From a call to the Saints in heaven and earth to rejoyce in Gods vengeance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, <hi>v.</hi> 20. which is further exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <hi>ch.</hi> 19. throughout.</p>
            <p>The Text is a Command to Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> leſt they partake with her in her fins, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of her Plagues.</p>
            <p>Three things ſhall be here conſidered.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The perſon commanding,</item>
               <item>2. The matter of the command, <hi>Come out &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The place from whence, <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The perſon commanding, is our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.: it was another voice di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the Angels, <hi>v.</hi> 2. this voice was from heaven, the Angels was on earth:
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:40317:71"/>and this perſon calls the godly his people, <hi>Come out of her my people,</hi> which no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture mioght do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The command is to come out of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon;</hi> the ſame words which were ſpoken to the <hi>Jews, Jer.</hi> 51. <hi>v.</hi> 6, 45. withdraw and Weparate your ſelves from her, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, at all times as to communion to withdraw from their worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>leaſt you communicate in her ſins,</hi> which they muſt needs do that joyn in her worſhip, and whenever there is opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſeparate your ſelves from the place and perſons; this the other part of the reaſon ſhows, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that ye receive not of her Plagues,</hi> which are to be the ſword, fire, and ſuch like waſting judgement, <hi>ch.</hi> 17.16. of which they muſt have their ſhare, that dwell in <hi>Babylon</hi> when theſe things fall upon them: and this was the meaning of the ſame command to the <hi>Jews, viz.</hi> that whilſt they lived in <hi>Babylon</hi> 70. years, they ſhould keep themſelves from her ldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries, and that they ſhould willingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from her, and return home when God ſhould open a door to them by <hi>Cyrus</hi> as he had promiſed.</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:40317:72"/>
            <p n="3">3. The place, <hi>out of her, viz. Babylon</hi> whoſe fall is foretold, <hi>v.</hi> 2. What this place is the former chapter declares paſt doubt to them that are willing to receive the truth.</p>
            <p>That it is a certain place and not the whole company of the wicked, as the <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> would perſwade us, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt.<note place="margin">In locum.</note> It is deſcribed as a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, a great Whore, <hi>v.</hi> 1.-4. under which figures Cities uſe to be ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Samaria, Ezech.</hi> 23.1.4. and ſhe hath a particular name written in her forehead, <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>Myſtery, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon the great</hi>—She is alſo called <hi>the Mother of Harlots, and abominations of the earth,</hi> which points out ſome place which ſhould be principal and ringleader in corruptions and perſecutions, <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6.</p>
            <p>That this place is the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> and not <hi>Conſtantinople, Jeruſalem,</hi> or any other City is alſo evident, becauſe ſhe is ſaid to be ſeated upon ſeven Mountains, and to have had ſeven ſorts of government, five paſt, one preſent and another to come, <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10, 11. which agree to no City but <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 18. it is added, that <hi>The woman is that great City which reigneth over the Kings of the earth, viz.</hi> in St. <hi>Johns</hi> time, which was none but <hi>Rome.</hi> Moreover that this was not Heathen <hi>Rome,</hi> but <hi>Rome</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:40317:72"/>declining both in Doctrine and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, appears, in that ſhe is taxed with Whoredome and drawing all the world to whoredome and fornication by her power and example; by which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth not expreſs the Idolatry of Heathens, but the Apoſtaſie of the Church to Idols, whereby ſhe breaketh her Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God her firſt husband.</p>
            <p>She is alſo called <hi>Myſtical Babylon, Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> for Tyranny and Idolatry, both of which old <hi>Babylon</hi> was mother to, in the declining world after the flood, and <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical</hi> becauſe not the ſame place; nor did ſhe openly bring in Idols, but under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of honouring Chriſt and his Saints: The Idolatry of Heathen <hi>Rome</hi> was no Myſtery.</p>
            <p>This woman alſo allureth the world to drink of the wine of her fornications, and thoſe that were backward ſhe compelled, till ſhe was drunk with the blood of Saints and Martyrs, inſomuch that the inhabitants of the earth generally wondred after the beaſt, <hi>v.</hi> 4, 8, but Heathen <hi>Rome</hi> was ſo far from impoſing her religion on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations (though ſhe puniſht the Chriſtians for departing from her religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) that ſhe left all Nations to their own way of worſhip, when ſhe had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:40317:73"/>them, even the <hi>Jews</hi> who were moſt different from all the reſt; yea it was her cuſtom to receive the worſhip and Gods of the conquered Nations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong her own ſolemnities, that ſo they might not provoke any Gods againſt them, and thus <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, <hi>Tiberius</hi> would have had our Saviour received into the number of the Roman gods; the Senate refuſed it becauſe they ſaid he would be God alone, and endure no companions with him: which further confirmeth that it was <hi>Rome</hi> Chriſtian and not Pagan which did impoſe her Idolatrous wrſhip upon the world.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, that it is <hi>Rome</hi> Papal, as it now is and hath been for many ages paſt, which is this <hi>Babylon,</hi> and not <hi>Rome</hi> when ſhe ſhall utterly renounce the Chriſtian faith in the end of the world as ſome Papiſts without ſhadow of reaſon fancy, is proved, in that ſhe is arrayed in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Scarlet, decked with gold and precious ſtones and pearls, which is the garb of the Pope and his Cardinals: In that ſhe is the Mother of fornications, Idolatries, through the earth, and that ſhe is drunk with the blood of Saints and Martyrs, <hi>Rome</hi> Papal having deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed far more Chriſtians, than ever Heathen <hi>Rome</hi> did.</p>
            <pb n="145" facs="tcp:40317:73"/>
            <p>And that the beaſt that carries this whore, the Roman State, is full of names of blaſphemy, <hi>v.</hi> 3. the blaſphemous ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and power which the Pope uſurpeth to himſelf and his Roman Church above any heathen that ever was.</p>
            <p>And eſpecially in that the ten horns upon the head of the beaſt that carries this Whore, which are ten Kingsariſing out of the diſſolution of the Roman Empire are ſaid to have received no Kingdom in <hi>Johns</hi> time, but to receive it one hour with the beaſt, <hi>v.</hi> 12. yea to give their power to the beaſt, to ſet him up, and maintain his Empire, and to be deluded by him, till God ſhall turn their hearts againſt him to deſtroy him, <hi>v.</hi> 13.-17. The beaſt himſelf alſo was to be the eighth head of the former great beaſt, and yet one of the ſeven, <hi>i. c.</hi> a new government in <hi>Rome,</hi> for the manner of it not much different from the preceding Emperours; all which are apparently fulfilled in the Pope and his adherents; For when <hi>Auguſtulus</hi> laid down the Empire, <hi>Ann. Chr.</hi> 476. there im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately appeared ten ſmall Kingdomes, ſometimes more, ſometimes fewer, in this Weſtern part of the world, and then the Pope began to uſurp the dominion of <hi>Rome,</hi> and both he and they grew up together, and ſtrengthened each other till they were all
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:40317:74"/>inſlaved by him, and had inabled him to trample Emperours under his feet: like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the declining or wane of Popedome in theſe too laſt ages hath been cauſed by the withdrawing of theſe very Princes from his ſubjection, whoſe Kingdomes were once provinces of <hi>Rome,</hi> and whoſe prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors had given their power to the Pope; and when a few more ſhall follow their example, the Pope will lofe his triple Crown.</p>
            <p>Theſe things thus explained the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is clear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> It is the command of Chriſt to all his people to withdraw from the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Papal <hi>Rome,</hi> as they would avoid joyning in her ſins, and to thoſe that have opportunity, to forſake the dwellings of <hi>Rome</hi> as they would eſcape her plagues.</p>
            <p>When the whole world after the flood apoſtatized from God and his worſhip, God ſingled out the family of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and in time increaſt them to a nation, to put his name, and to keep up his worſhip, among them: for this the reſt eſpecially their neighbours in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> hated, and oppoſed them, and the heads of this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition were <hi>Egypt, Niniveh,</hi> and at laſt <hi>Babylon</hi> in <hi>Chaldea,</hi> which ſwallowed up all her neighbours; Thus there was a long conteſt betwixt the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> who
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:40317:74"/>adhered to God and pure religion, and <hi>Babylon</hi> which was become the head of the Pagan Apoſtaſie in the <hi>Eaſt:</hi> In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the Goſpel was no ſooner planted and ſpread throughout the <hi>Weſtern</hi> world, but there began a defection to Idolatry in the worſhip of Saints and Angels, and after ſome while <hi>Rome</hi> became the head of this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſie, and for above 1 thouſand years paſt, there hath been a continual conteſt betwixt a purer part of Chriſts Church ſcattered through divers Countries, and this <hi>Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Babylon;</hi> a certain number ſpecified by one hundred forty four thouſand, <hi>Rev</hi> 14.1. have kept themſelves pure from the whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>Rome,</hi> they were Virgins and followed the Lamb whitherſoever he went, and with them the Roman beaſt hath continually made war, and ſtill ſeeks to deſtroy them out of the earth: now all that would be the faithful ſervants of Chriſt muſt joyn with this ſmall perſecuted company, and neither comply with, nor ſubmit to <hi>Rome,</hi> nor connive at her power and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, as they would not be found guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of her Apoſtaſie, and be ſwept away in her deſtruction.</p>
            <p>To prove this, becauſe we ſpeak to them who are already ſeparated from <hi>Rome,</hi> it will be ſufficient to clear theſe 2 Queſtions, which being cleared will alſo prove the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:40317:75"/>duty of others to ſeparate from her, who yet either adhere to, or lean towards her.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Queſtion,</hi> whether there was a juſt ground for the Poteſtants to ſeparate from the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Whether there can be any reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Proteſtants to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In which I ſhall be brief, becauſe a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is in a ſort laid for it in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether Proteſtants did upon juſt and neceſſary grounds ſeparate from the communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in her worſhip and diſcipline?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> They did, which I thus prove.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the rule of the Chriſtian faith. The Church is a holy Common-wealth under the government of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and he governs it by his laws contained in the holy Scriptures; theſe are the rule of their worſhip and obedience to him, <hi>Math.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20. He that alters this rule, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth the fundamental conſtitution of the Church; But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered this rule; they teach the Scriptures to be a defective, inſufficient rule, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they joyn to them the Apocryphal books of the Old Teſtament and the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the Church (which alſo they
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:40317:75"/>receive and reject at their pleaſure,) De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Councils, and decretals and deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Popes; all theſe together are the perfect rule that the Papiſts acknowledge and pretend to; I ſay, pretend, becauſe the Scripture hath little ſhare in it, when it comes to Tryal; hereby they have made a new foundation of the Church, both of faith and practice; For it is not ſufficient that we believe and practiſe all that is in the Canonical Scriptures, but we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and obey the Apocryphal writings and unwritten Traditions, as of the ſame authority with the Bible; thus the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent</hi> hath determined, as was ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before: This altereth the very conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Church, and ſubjecteth it to men inſtead of Chriſt; and this is the root of all apoſtaſie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the Papiſts pretend their Pope or Church to be above the Scriptures, and to put an authentick authority on them and their ſenſe; Thus all our faith and obedience is reſolved into the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men. That the Papiſts pretend the Pope, their Council, or Church, to be above the Scriptures, cannot be denied, they give the authority and authentick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Scriptures, 'tis from their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that the Bible is received, and if they pleaſed they might cauſe it to be laid
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:40317:76"/>aſide; it cannot be known (they ſay) that the Scriptures are Gods word, but that their Church declares it; nor is any ſenſe or meaning to be fixt upon, as the certain ſenſe of any Scripture, but what they determine to be the meaning of the place. Accordingly the <hi>Trent.</hi> Council out of their great power have determined the vulgar Latin Tranſlation of the Bible to be authentick, and equal to the Greek and Hebrew originals,<note place="margin">Council of Trent, Seſ. <hi>4</hi>
               </note> though their own authors acknowledge it to be moſt falſe, defective, and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things ridiculous: Now then our faith is not ultimately reſolved into the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, we do not believe and obey, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we know and are ſure from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that this is the mind of God, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Pope or Church declare it to be the mind of God; yea though the words of Scripture plainly condemn what they teach, or though the Tranſlation of a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be contrary to the original which was indited by the ſpirit of God immediately; yet if they ſay this is the meaning of the place and the true tranſlation of it, we muſt believe it; The foundation then of all our faith and obedience is the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Church or Pope.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But they are infallible they ſay.</p>
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:40317:76"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This they can never prove; but if they were, if I muſt believe meerly upon their Teſtimony, and ſaying they are infallible, my faith is ſtill reſolved into the witneſs of men: their teſtimony con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning themſelves is but a humane Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, they do not, cannot prove it by any divine, infallible proof; therefore my faith and obedience muſt ultimately peſolve into humane authority. The Apoſtles were infallible, yet had not they dominion over the faith of the Church, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.24. to command what ſhould be believed and practiſed; but they proved by infallible and divine. Teſtimony of miracles and gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, that what they taught came from God, and ſo the belief of the people was built upon the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of God to the Apoſtles doctrine, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4, 5. the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was in demonſtration of the ſpirit and of power. That their faith might not ſtand in the wiſdom of men, but in the power of God:</hi> If their faith had been grounded upon the Apoſtles own Teſtimony of his ſelf that he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, and upon his determination concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Scripture or doctrine out of his own wiſdom, though he had ſeemed to prove it ſtrangely, their faith had ſtood upon the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoty &amp; wiſdom of man; but therefore their faith was built on God, becauſe his ſpirit
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:40317:77"/>did powerfully demonſtrate what the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle preacht to be from God; therefore unleſs the Papiſts can prove their infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility by miracles, and demonſtration of the ſpirit, theirs is but a humane Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſo we know it is, and a falſe one too: and therefore it is an intolerable abuſe to take the Church off from faith and obedience to Chriſt as the head command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ruling her, and from the holy Spirit, as inditing and confirming the holy Scriptures, and to ſubject her to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and determinations of fallible and ſometimes moſt wicked men: To let paſs that the Papiſts themſelves not being agreed who is the infallible ſupreme judge, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope, Council, or the whole Church, no man of them hath any ſure foundation, for his Faith: If they ſay the Scripture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares who is the ſupreme infallible Judge; I anſwer that Judge muſt again tell us what is the meaning of that Scripture; The Pope ſaith it means him, the Council and Church ſay it means them; here are three preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to ſupreme and infallible authority, and to interpret the Scripture; which ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever a man adheres to, it is two to one but he is miſtaken; however here is no way to determine who is the infallible Judge, unleſs there be infallible marks and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of it given by God, and then they
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:40317:77"/>are of the ſupreme authority, and neither Pope, Council, nor Church themſelves; but ſuch they can never produce. Thus the whole matter is but an inconſiſtent jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle to bring the Church into ſubjection to the Pope.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> takes away the Scriptures from the people, yea and alloweth the Clergy themſelves the uſe of the corrupt, vulgar Tranſlation of the Bible only. <hi>Faith comes by hearing and hearing by the word of God, Rom.</hi> 10.14. How then ſhall the people get Faith or grow in it, when they muſt not have the Scriptures to read themſelves, nor have them read to them by their teachers, but in an unknown tongue, and that Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation ſo corrupt alſo, that if any of them ſhould underſtand Latin, they would yet have much difficulty to find the truth. The Scriptures are Chriſts Law whereby he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns his Church, and the peoples <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> the Charter of all their priviledges, and of all Gods promiſes ſpiritual and temporal; to take this from them is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them, both of the rule of their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and of the foundation of all their faith and hope in God: This is not to be endured upon any pretence whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Becauſe they impoſe the celebration of Gods worſhip in an unknown tongue the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:40317:78"/>Papiſts celebrate their prayers, Sacraments, and ſinging of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> all in Latin, which as they know the people underſtand not, ſo they would not have them underſtand it; by this means the people are deprived of all true worſhip; For worſhip is the reverence and affection of the ſoul to God, either in aſcribing honour to him, or deſiring of him and truſting in him for whatever we need. This it is impoſſible man ſhould give to God in and by thoſe words and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which he underſtandeth not, which for what he knows may blaſpheme God, or beg a curſe inſtead of a bleſſing, which as managed by illiterate Prieſts oftentimes are nonſenſe and ſignifie nothing, and ſometimes contrary to ſound Doctrine, yea may at all times for what the people know be directed to an Idol or a Devil inſtead of God. For preaching of the word the Papiſts pretend but little to it: And thus the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church is a Church of Chriſt, which acknowledgeth not him for her head and Governour, nor his word for her rule and Law, nor his worſhip for her practice; but ſabjecteth her ſelf to a wicked man under the name of Chriſts Vicar, taketh his will for her Law, and his inſtitutions for her worſhip, without Queſtion and without underſtanding; This is an abuſe Jot to be tolerated.</p>
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:40317:78"/>
            <p n="5">5. The Idolary that the Papiſts impoſe on the Church; the Apoſtle is expreſs, <hi>You cannot partake of the Table of the Lord and the Table of Devils, the Cup of the Lord and the cup of Devils,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> wor-10.20, 21. and theſe Devils, he ſaith, are ſhipped in Idols by Idolaters, with whom therefore we muſt have no communion; now the greateſt part of the Papiſts worſhip conſiſts in the worſhip and invocation of Saints, Angels, and the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and their waſer-God, which they practiſe upon the very ſame grounds on which the Heathens worſhipt their Idols, and therefore are Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters as well as the Heathens: they ſay they do not worſhip them as God; the Heathens ſaid the ſame and as truly; but they do aſcribe to them the praiſe, truſt, homage and ſubjection, fear and reverence, which is due only to God which is above the condition and deſert of our fellow Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who depend upon God, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſt as much as we; and this doth take off the Heart from God, and makes men believe that the Saints and Angels are nearer to us, more merciful, more ready to help us than God is, and more concerned for our good than our bleſſed Lord whoſe whole work it is to redeem and interceed for us.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Their impoſing the belief of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:40317:79"/>and worſhip of the bread in the Sacrament: Moſt of our <hi>Marian</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs were put to death upon this point on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their not believing the real preſence (as they Papiſts call it) of Chriſt in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, <hi>i. e.</hi> that the bread was ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally turned into the body of Chriſt. If men would impoſe upon us the belief of the leaſt untruth, though in natural or civil things, we muſt not ſubmit to them, much leſs when they impoſe ſuch an untruth as this Tianſubſtantiation, which is againſt the plain letter of Scripture, which ſaith, that Chriſt did not only take, which was before Conſecration, but alſo that he gave bread and wine (to be eaten and drunk by his diſciples) which was after they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.22, 23. which is alſo againſt our ſenſes; the eye, the ſmell, the touch and taſte, all witneſſing the Elements to be ſtill bread and wine; againſt Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, which teacheth ſuch a change of one body into another, eſpecially ſo ſmall a one as that of a Wafer into ſo large as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, to be abſolutely impoſſible; yea and againſt common reaſon, which knows whence the bread and wine came, how they were made, how they go into the ſtomach, are digeſted, refreſh, and are carried off like other food: ſhould ſuch a Paradox be admitted, there can be no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:40317:79"/>in any thing; For by the pretence of ſuch a change or miracle, all evidence may be evaded; and ſo the Apoſtles that ſaw Chriſt in the body, heard him, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him, both before and after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, might (for what we know) be all miſtaken; and all the witneſſes of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles that confirm both Teſtaments, might all failin their ſenſe and judgement of things, and ſo nothing be certain in Religion, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is continually in innumerable places ſuch a prodigie as the Hoſt, which is as they ſay the glorified body of Chriſt now in Heaven, and yet ſenſe and reaſon take it to be a bit of bread; what may they not perſwade and impoſe on people, that can prevail with them to believe this? The worſhipping of the bread doth alſo deſtroy the nature and uſe of the Sacrament, where inſtead of a comfortable remembrance of Chriſt and his death, to increaſe faith in him, and love to him, men are taught only igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly to worſhip a bit of bread, and that with more ſolemnity, than Chriſt himſelf was honoured with on earth.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Becauſe they take away the cup from the people in the Sacrament, hereby they take upon them to alter Chriſts inſtitution at their pleaſure; they deprive the people not only of one part of the Sacrament, but in ſo doing wholly obſcure the meaning of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament;
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:40317:80"/>for ſeeing they break not the bread but give it whole, nor pour out the wine, nor ſuffer the people to ſee and drink it; the people have no repreſentation of the death of Chriſt, neither of the breaking or bruiſing of his body, nor ſhedding his blood; and in this the Papiſts are moſt inſolent of any other their Corruptions; for that their Councils of<note n="a" place="margin">Seſſ. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Conſtance</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">Seſſ. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Trent</hi> do acknowledge, that Chriſt gave both Elements to his diſciples, and that the Primitive Church continued the like cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom for many ages, and yet they can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to alter it upon trivial reaſons.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Papiſts greatly obſcure the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Juſtification; the Goſpel is the glad tydings of peace, the word of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. ch. 19, 20. <hi>v.</hi>
               </note> that God is in Chriſt reconciling the world to himſelf is the chief thing committed to the Miniſters of the Goſpel; if therefore this be obſcured, the Goſpel is in a great meaſure rendred ineffectual, and the Miniſtry uſeleſs for the end it was appointed for. It is the chief enquiry of ſinful man, what he ſhould do to be ſaved, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.31. and on this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends all his worſhip of God; for till man be reconciled to God, he cannot wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him acceptably, nor can he truſt, love
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:40317:80"/>and fear God aright, unleſs he know upon what grounds, and in what way God will have this done. If we loſe the doctrine of Juſtification, we loſe the ſubſtance of the Goſpel and of all Religion: Now this the Papiſts do obſcure ſo much, that a man can ſcarce tell amidſt their Doctrines, what Chriſt hath done for him, and what he muſt expect from Chriſt. They ſay a natural man improving the gifts of nature, doth in ſome fort merit the grace and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and when he hath that grace he doth <hi>ex condigno</hi> properly and of due debt merit the continuance of Gods favour, and heaven it ſelf; yea, over and above may merit for other men: and if a man do commit ſins after converſion, his volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry penances, his patient bearing of Gods corrections in this world, and Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory in the next, together with alms-deeds, faſtings and ſuch good works, do make full ſatisfaction for all theſe ſins; and he that wants penance and ſatisfactions of his own, may be ſupplied out of the treaſury of the Church by Maſſes and the Popes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences. Now this is not only the doctrine of Schoolmen, but the chief part of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and worſhip among them, and the chief things the Prieſts teach and are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd about.</p>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:40317:81"/>
            <p n="9">9. The Popes claim of ſupremacy is blaſphemous, and not to be ſubmitted to by the Churches: Under the Goſpel Chriſt hath appointed no high Prieſt to whom all Miniſters ſhould be ſubject, no place of worſhip to which all Nations ſhould repair, no Mother Church on which they ſhould depend, none to be his Vicar on earth: but all this the Pope and Church of <hi>Rome</hi> claim and uſurp, which tendeth to bring all the Churches on earth into bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage to them, and to exclude the conduct of the ſpirit in the Miniſters and Churches, as if it were peculiar to them only; it is alſo a power which no Creature is capable of, and derogates from the honour of Chriſt, who doth by his Godhead, ſpirit and word, preſide in, govern and guide his whole Church.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Becauſe the Papiſts have wholly changed the diſcipline of the Goſpel into a pompous, worldly Polity. Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Paſtors and teachers for the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Saints, till they all come to the perfect man in Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12, 13. but the Papiſts have changed this into a viſible, worldly Monarchy, though under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Religion and the name of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, of which the Pope is the head, his Cardinals Princes, all his Prieſts and Clergy
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:40317:81"/>officers and Factors for him to hold the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men in ſubjection to him, and to keep Princes and their Kingdoms in homage, and tributary to his Coffers. By all theſe things it appears that the Papiſts have quite altered both the foundation and ſuperſtructure of the Church of God, and the government of his houſe, and retained little more than the name of Chriſt, his Church and Goſpel; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was neceſſary they ſhould withdraw from them who had any care of the honour of God, or their own ſalvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> The Papiſts Object, that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants acknowledge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be a true Church, and therefore not to be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Suppoſe it were a true Church, are not other true Churches alſo? What obligation ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon all Churches to be members of &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> more than on the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf to be a member of any other true Church? ſurely none from the notion of a true Church, ſeeing all Churches of Chriſt that are true, are at leaſt equal with her in this attribute. If they ſay that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath the Primacy of all Churches and dominion over them from <hi>Peter</hi> the head of the Church, this is but to beg what they can never prove; that <hi>Peter</hi> had the headſhip of the Church committed to him and his ſucceſſors, and which is denyed of their own Council of <hi>Conſtance, Seſſ.</hi> 15.</p>
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:40317:82"/>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth retain the profeſſion of Chriſtanity, the general creeed, and the holy Scriptures, however they deviate from them in their expoſitions and practice; therefore the Proteſtants dare not deny it abſolutely to be a Church of Chriſt; but that he may be ſtill ſtriving with it and may have many in it, who may keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the great corruptions of it, even as the 7000. in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who had not bowed the knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> and ſo ſhe may continue a Church in this ſenſe, and in this State till her finall rejection and deſtruction, nevertheleſs they unanimouſly agree that ſhe is an Idolatrous, Apoſtatical Church, under great and fatal corruptions, though ſhe hath not quite forſaken the name of Chriſt, or he utterly forſaken her, as the ten Tribes under <hi>Jeroboam</hi> became idolatrous and Apoſtatical, and are ſaid to have worſhipped Devils in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the Calves, though they pretended them to repreſent <hi>Jehovah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.15. and when they were in this ſtate of backſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the people as well as the Prieſts and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, that did ſet their hearts to ſeek the Lord God of their fathers, forſook them and went to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to ſacrifice, and joyned themſelves to <hi>Judah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.13.17.16. and in the time of his ſucceſſours thoſe that were upright and had opportunity did ſtill reſort to <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:40317:82"/>to worſhip; whence the Idolatrous Prieſts are complained of for laying wait and Nets for them in <hi>Miſpah</hi> and <hi>Tabor:</hi> and this they did notwithſtanding that God did ſtill contend with <hi>Iſrael</hi> by his Prophets, and ſent many eminent ones to them; as <hi>Elijah, Eliſha, Hoſea, Jonah,</hi> with many others, to call them back again to himſelf, to continue to warn and invite them to repentance even untill their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſion and captivity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A 2. Queſtion is whether there may be any reconciliation of Poteſtants to or with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And here I muſt diſtinguiſh betwixt particular perſons, members of that Church, and the body of the Church it ſelf. There are many particular perſons in the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Communion, that be wail their corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that complain of their bondage, and are moderate toward Proteſtants; for theſe we may have charity, reſpect and compaſſion; but to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the general commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and ſociety of Papiſts under the Pope the ir head, there may be nocommunion or recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe they have redreſſed none of their errors and corruptions, for which the Proteſtants at firſt forſook them. If our firſt ſeparation from <hi>Rome</hi> was juſt and neceſſary, ſo it is ſtill, for they have not mended, or redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed any of the grounds of our ſeparation: but on the contrary when they were intreated and
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:40317:83"/>in a ſort compelled to call the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> to compoſe matters, beſides the many unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy arts they uſed to have men choſen to their mind and of their own party, they did ſeverally confirm every error in doctrine, and corruption in worſhip, which the Proteſtants accuſed them of, and Anathematized all that held the doctrine of the Proteſtants, and as if this were not enough, their Prieſts are all to be ſworn to maintain this Council, and a Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm was ordered to be compoſed out of it to be the ſtandard of the Doctrine of that Church, which was done accordingly.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As they have not, ſo they cannot mend, or alter any thing conſiderable. The conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Roman Papal Church depends on the corruptions they maintain and practiſe. Should their Clergy marry, they would not be at the Popes command: ſhould they lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide private Maſſes, image worſhip, and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, their Prieſts would loſe a great part of their maintenance; and the Pope a great jewel in his Crown, <hi>viz.</hi> the power of cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing Saints and freeing ſouls from Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: and if the people ſhould have the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and publick ſervice in their own tongue, they would quickly diſcern the corruptions of their Church, and impoſtures of their Pope; above all, ſhould they alter any thing of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment decreed by the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> which was alſo confirmed by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the 4th. it
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:40317:83"/>would ſhake the foundation of the Church the Popes infallibility: for either the Council and Pope <hi>Pius</hi> erred in their decrees, or that Pope muſt err who alters any thing of thoſe decrees: hence it was, that the Pope and Council of <hi>Trent</hi> would not yield ſo much as the cup in the Lords ſupper to the Laity at any time or in any caſe though greatly importuned to do it by the Emperor <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the 1. and his ſon <hi>Maximilian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the body of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt or man of ſin, ſhe hath made him her head and hath eſpouſed her ſelf to him as her Lord, the whole religion of Popery is fitted only to exalt the Pope and his Clegy; and cheat the people both of the knowledge of God, and of their money. To unite with <hi>Rome</hi> is to joyn our ſelves with a company of Rebels and fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives from Chriſt, that have conſpired againſt him, and ſet them up another King and Lord.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Rome</hi> haht of long time and doth main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an oppoſition againſt the Churches of Chriſt. She contends for the univerſal head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Pope, ſhe decreeth and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth (as far as ſhe can) the deſtruction of all Hereticks, <hi>i. e.</hi> of all that will not ſubmit to her corruptions, for about 900 years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſtill attempts the ſame. To joyn with <hi>Rome</hi> is to condemn all the Confeſſors and Martyrs, that have ſuffered by them, and
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:40317:84"/>to bring the guilt of their blood upon our ſelves, as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Math.</hi> 23.35. all the righteous blood that was ſhed upon the earth from <hi>Abel</hi> to <hi>Zacharias</hi> ſhould be requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of that generation, becauſe they perſiſted in the footſteps of their fathers, and were of the ſame body and ſucceſſion with them that ſhed that blood.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Rome</hi> is appointed for deſtruction. That State or Polity, that City and people are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt to be utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroyed, as in the 17, 18, 19. of the <hi>Rev.</hi> at large: and their deſtruction is not threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned conditionally in caſe they repent not, as it is to other Nations; but it is abſolutely fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, as of a people abhorred of the Lord, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken and given over by him, becauſe they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook him firſt. Chriſt hath declared war againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> which he will purſue till he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered her, and triumphed over her: therefore there may not be that deſire or attempt of union with her as with other backſliding Churches. Gods people are called to come out of <hi>Babylon</hi> upon pain of their deſtruction, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are not to make peace with her. Who would joyn with a periſhing Church, with a Party devoted to deſtruction, and with a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing religion? whereas Chriſt will have a Church pure and triumphant, which ſhall ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive and triumph over <hi>Babylon, Rev.</hi> 19.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40317:84"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
